<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Europe's chains broke, or, A sure and speedy project to rescue her from the present usurpations of the tyrant of France</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 153 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 85 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38742</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3418</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27969</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10285522</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10285522</idno>
            <idno type="VID">44821</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38742)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44821)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1383:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Europe's chains broke, or, A sure and speedy project to rescue her from the present usurpations of the tyrant of France</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>166 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ric. Baldwin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Trinity College Library, Cambridge University.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Europe --  History --  1648-1715.</term>
               <term>Europe --  Politics and government --  1648-1715.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:44821:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:44821:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Europe's Chains Broke;</hi> OR, A Sure and Speedy PROJECT TO Reſcue <hi>Her</hi> from the PRESENT USURPATIONS OF THE Tyrant of <hi>FRANCE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Ric. Baldwin,</hi> near the <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford-Arms</hi> in <hi>Warwick-Lane.</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:44821:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:44821:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Europe's Chains Broke;</hi> OR, A Sure and Speedy Project TO Reſcue <hi>Her</hi> from the PRESENT USURPATIONS, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Civil Wars in a State, have always been conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as the greateſt and moſt dangerous Evils; they are like thoſe internal Diſeaſes of Man, which for the moſt part af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a Languiſhing Life, are termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated by Death.</p>
            <p>If we paſs from Particulars, to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:44821:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:44821:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:44821:4"/> the Generality of <hi>Europe,</hi> is ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry likely, that that part of the World had not found it ſelf ready to periſh under the Cruel Power of the Capital Enemy of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom, as it was very near du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the laſt Siege of <hi>Vienna;</hi> if all the Princes of Chriſtendom had been in good Intelligence, and in a ſincere <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> and had unanimouſly endeavour'd to Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe their Common Enemy, who then durſt not to have advanc'd ſo far in <hi>Europe,</hi> if he had been drawn in only through the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>underſtanding of the Chriſtian Princes, and not Invited into it, and puſh'd on by a moſt Chriſtian Prince, the Eldeſt Son of the Church; who to facilitate his Paſſage, has made him a way, through Rebellion, in <hi>Hungary;</hi> which he has fomented to that very end, and maintain'd by mony, and Officers that he has ſent thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in the Deſign after the taking
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:44821:4"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f that City, the Imperial Sear, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſhare, for a Beginning, with the Grand Seignior his Ally, all <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y;</hi> which the Sultan had agreed to, is freely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. did ſeek <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fter it, with a deſign however to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eceive one another, and in the end <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>revail over his Companion; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <hi>French</hi> King to do after wards, that which the Emperor does at this time, to drive the <hi>Turks</hi> back to <hi>Adrianople.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But before we paſs to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance of our <hi>Europe,</hi> let us mention the Dangers it has been in theſe late years, and let us lay down for a ſure Foundation, and an indiſputable Truth, that the Chriſtians Diſunion has given opportunity to the Infidels to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Tributary <hi>Valachia, Tranſilva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, Moldavia,</hi> and divers other Territories, and in the laſt place to Invade <hi>Hungaria;</hi> which has oblig'd a great number of poor miſerable Chriſtians not only to fall
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:44821:5"/>into ſlavery, but to make Ship wrack in the Chriſtian Religion and I dare aſſert, that had it no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> been for the preſſing Offers o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>France</hi> by the means of <hi>Teckeley</hi> the Sultan had never broke th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Truce, nor durſt to have come to ſet up the Standard of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſter <hi>Mahomet,</hi> before the Capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal City of <hi>Germany,</hi> as he did in the Year 1683. while his Ally was in <hi>Alſatia</hi> with an Army of 40000 Men, ready to Invade the Empire, (which the Grand Seig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior for his part had favour'd) ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to make himſelf Maſter of the whole, or to render Tributary that which he could not have kept, and by that means mount ſtep by ſtep to the Monarchy of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> little troubling himſelf about the Evils which Chriſtendom had ſuffer'd, neither by the barbarouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Army, or of thoſe of the <hi>Turks;</hi> ſo that <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great had but gratified his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:44821:5"/>and his Paſſion of Ruling lely.</p>
            <p>Thus on all ſides, <hi>Europe</hi> did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e it ſelf on the Edge of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pices, and in an Abiſs of Evils, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hence it could not be got out of gain but by a ſtroke from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; not knowing which Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to chuſe, the Ambition of the one, or the Intereſt of the other, the <hi>French</hi> Tiranny, or the <hi>Mahometan</hi> ſlavery, finding them hoth equally Unjuſt, Barbarous, and Inhumane, and very oppoſite to Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>There are but few Perſons in <hi>Europe,</hi> never ſo little Rational, but have been inform'd of all the Advances of <hi>France,</hi> of <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV's Proceeding, of his Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and of his Paſſion to Rule over his Equals, and to render the Kings and Princes of the Earth his Tributaries; and to ſpeak it in plainer Terms, to become the ſole Monarch of the World: As there
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:44821:6"/>is but one Son; boaſting already of giving Peace to whom he pleas'd and to Exterminate or Bomb all that ſhould oppoſe themſelves to his <hi>good Will and Pleaſure,</hi> and like to another <hi>Jupiter,</hi> caſt his Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-Bolts on all that durſt raiſe themſelves againſt him, deſigning, like God, to Rule over Conſciences as well as over the Inheritances.</p>
            <p>But the Ambitious Man, who raiſes himſelf on high and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous places, not conſidering much how to get down again, never turns his Eyes on the ſide of the Precipice; he runs to his deſire, as if he were in good Intelligence with Fortune, and as if the World was conducted by Fate in lieu of Divine Providence. Mean time, we ſee that God confounds his Deſigns, and ſtops him frequently in the midſt of his Career, forcing him with ſhame, to quit a way in which he thought to have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinu'd with Glory. <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:44821:6"/>had reſolv'd within himſelf to mount on the Imperial Throne, in the ſtrange imagination he had, that having attain'd thither, not only the Empire, but all the reſt of <hi>Europe</hi> would bow under his Orders, and at the approach of his Armies; in effect, he ſpar'd nothing to compaſs it, with a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to Sacrifice all to his Paſſion, and to deſtroy all that ſhould oppoſe it ſelf to his Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur. To this purpoſe, he began to oppreſs the one, to deceive the other, and to entertain a third by fair and deceitful Promiſes, ſparing neither ſpecious Titles nor Penſions, to thoſe which he thought might be uſeful to him, by thoſe means, giving to ſome an Apple to play with, while he made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Maſter over the others, and in a manner ſeparated <hi>Europe</hi> from it ſelf, and every Prince from his Ally, as well as from his true and real Intereſts, which has ever been
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:44821:7"/>by all means to maintain an Equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity amongſt the Princes of <hi>Europe,</hi> that their Forces being equally di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed, Chriſtendom might be preſerv'd in good Peace, and every State in its own Rights and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties: Seeing that from the aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the one, follows the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of the other, as we have ſeen; ſince when <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt weaken'd his Power by the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of his Kingdoms, and after that, his Son <hi>Philip</hi> permitting part of thoſe Provinces which had been left to his ſhare to be taken from him; ſo was his Fall the Riſe of the <hi>French</hi> Kings, who have inſenſibly got the ſtart of their Equals, and have got ſtep by ſtep up to the Supreme Degree, which we have ſeen in this laſt Reign of <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. who du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a long time has not ceas'd from gaining Victory on Victory; taking of Town upon Town; and as a boundleſs Torrent, carry all
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:44821:7"/>before him which oppos'd his Courſe, his Violence not being to be ſtopp'd but by a Stroke from H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aven, and by a Voice iſſuing from the <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ittiſh</hi> Throne, crying out, <hi>Nec plu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ultra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. who had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, in his hopes, devour'd a good part of <hi>Europe,</hi> which lay groaning, and as it were over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by the evils of a continual War, has been, as it is not to be doubted, extremly ſurpriz'd, to ſee himſelf ſtopp'd on the ſudden, by that ſurprizing Change which has ſo lately happen'd in <hi>England;</hi> and who can doubt, but that this change of Soveraigns has been a Mortal Blow to him, ſeeing that by that means he not only ſees his Great and Ambitious Deſig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd, and in lieu of a near Ally and intimate Friend, he finds on the Throne none but an unrecon-cilable Enemy, burning with Zeal for the Preſervation of <hi>Europe,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:44821:8"/>and with a deſire of Puniſhing th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Uſurper? and that which is ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> more ſenſible to <hi>France,</hi> is, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this New Monarch will not fail o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> being Seconded by all the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Princes. We have ſeen <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in changing of Maſter, to make the face of the Affairs o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Europe</hi> change alſo, eſpecially in the Low-Countries, the decree of their Ruine having been determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned between the Two Kings, <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. and <hi>James</hi> the II. after that <hi>France</hi> had long con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd, the United Provinces a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the only Obſtacle that could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent it from Conquering the reſt of <hi>Europe;</hi> well knowing, that thoſe States would at all times Oppoſe themſelves to the Ruine of their Neighbours, puſh'd on by a Motive of Generoſity, of Equity, and of Intereſt alſo: Therefore the King of <hi>France,</hi> could not perceive which way he ſhould go about to overcome his Opponents, but
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:44821:8"/>in mining and in deſtroying to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally thoſe Provinces, thereby ſhut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them out of the power of hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring him, or of oppoſing his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, and that he could not do with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>England</hi>'s conſent: Wherefore after the death of <hi>Charles</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, he ſo dextrouſly did embark King <hi>James</hi> in his Deſign, and ſet him at variance with his Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, through Religious Motives, by ridiculous demands of the abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of the <hi>Teſt</hi> and <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> (which had been eſtabliſhed for the ſupport of the Kingdom, and the preſervation of the Eſtabliſh'd Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,) <hi>France</hi> was aſſur'd, that by that means it ſhould ſet the King and Parliament out of power or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uniting again, and that by thoſe means <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. ſhould ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige that Prince whom he led by the Noſe, to apply himſelf to him for Mony, which he certainly knew the Parliament would refuſe him; that in caſe they ſhould grant it to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:44821:9"/>him, it ſhould be on ſuch conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which the King would not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept: And thus that ill advis'd P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nce would not fail to turn him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf towards <hi>France</hi> as he has done, and to let himſelf be obſeded and won by fair but falſe Promiſes, to render him abſolute Maſter over his People and his Parliament; with which <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. has ſo long fed and entertain'd with dexterity the weak Imagination of his Ally, that he has lull'd him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep into a Lethargy, very oppoſite to his right Intereſt, to that of his People, and even to that of all <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> of which it may be ſaid, That <hi>England</hi> holds the Scales.</p>
            <p>In the year 1672. <hi>France</hi> was already working on her project a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the United States, through the means of <hi>England,</hi> if we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with what weakneſs <hi>Charles</hi> the Second permitted himſelf to be ty'd up by thoſe Treaties he made, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to ſo many Obligations which
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:44821:9"/>he had to the ſaid States, and of his particular Intereſt, feeding himſelf with hopes of a ſhare in thoſe ſaid Provinces before they were taken. With what weakneſs did the ſame Prince ſell to <hi>France</hi> the Town of <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> and behold with his Arms folded <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. take the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal places of the <hi>Spaniſh Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands,</hi> not only <hi>Cambray Valencienne,</hi> S. <hi>Omers, Erre,</hi> but ſo many others al-alſo, which were as ſo many <hi>bulwarks</hi> to ſtay the fury of <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV.</p>
            <p>And ever after the Peace of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meguen,</hi> have not whole Provinces ſubmitted to the <hi>French</hi> Yoke? And while that under the ſhelter of that Peace, other Soveraigns had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banded their Forces, <hi>France</hi> alone kept his Arms, becauſe it knew what it was hatching, and what it deſign'd to do. The Town of <hi>Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>embourg</hi> was a Thorn in its ſide, and it would be Maſter of it; and <hi>Charles</hi> the Second was as little mov'd or it, as if he had been pay'd, to let him do and ſay nothing, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:44821:10"/>behold unconcern'd that place taken from the <hi>Spaniard.</hi> Free <hi>Europe</hi> which little by little ſaw one Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince after another, and one Town after another ſubmitted to <hi>France,</hi> did frequently caſt its Eye towards the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> in hopes to receive ſome relief from that part; but <hi>France</hi> had ſo well taken its meaſures there, that before that Illuſtrious Body was aſſembled, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Lords at the ſound of <hi>Louis d'Ors,</hi> were become deaf to the Complaints of the generality, and ſome amongſt them had even loſt the uſe of Speech, and were become motionleſs for the publick good, and that of the Nation; and ſo ſoon as the Houſe of Commons began to harp on that ſtring, the King made uſe of his Authority to prorogue them to another time; and ſo bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs run in the ſame courſe again, and gave leave to <hi>France</hi> to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue its way, to gain Conqueſt on Conqueſt: In the mean time the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:44821:10"/>true <hi>Engliſh men,</hi> who are the moſt jealous of their Liberties of any Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, were forc'd to be ſilent, and quietly behold themſelves hedg'd in on all ſides without oppoſing it, nor daring to complain. Thoſe that were lukewarm would frequently ask, Why the <hi>Spaniards</hi> and the <hi>Imperialiſts,</hi> who had moſt intereſt in it, did not oppoſe themſelves to that T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rrent, and to thoſe <hi>French</hi> Conqueſts? I confeſs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that if they could have done it alone, they ought to have gone about it, and they can never be excus'd for having neglected it; but thoſe who know a little the Affairs of the World, are not ignorant of the miſery <hi>Spain</hi> is fallen into, during the minority of a King; and that the <hi>Netherlands</hi> are far remote from the Empire, which has many Heads, and which of truth cannot aſſiſt them without its Allyes that are neareſt to thoſe Provinces, who are the King of <hi>England,</hi> and the States of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Provinces.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:44821:11"/>
            <p>The Emperor has continually the <hi>Turks</hi> at his doors, over which he is to keep a ſtrict watch at all times. Beſides, as I have already mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the Empire's compos'd of divers Members, who have each their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign and their different Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, and therefore a long time is required, and divers Springs muſt play, to ſet ſo great a Machine go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and frequently before the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of it be taken, <hi>France</hi> has done its do, and then it ſpeaks of Peace and of Accommodation, by which means <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. has for the moſt part kept his Conqueſts, if they deſerve that Name; after which every one retires home &amp; disbands. <hi>France</hi> makes ſhew to do the ſame; and if it acquieſces ſo far to dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band ſome Troops in one part of the Kingdom, it raiſes others in another; and thus remains ſtill in the ſame poſture to do miſchief, ready to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt ſome new thing ſo ſoon as it finds any favourable opportunity.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:44821:11"/>In that interval <hi>France</hi> did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main quiet, it had its Emiſſaries in all the Courts of <hi>Germany,</hi> who uſing the ſlight of hand, acquir'd thereby many Creatures; it is a Maxime which has long ſince ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded well with them, and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly at the Court of <hi>England</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the laſt Reigns; &amp; thoſe Emiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries have labour'd with ſo much zeal and heat, and return'd ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently to the charge, doubling the Doſe when there was occaſion, that they often ſucceeded, and by thoſe means have oppoſed themſelves to the beſt Deſigns which the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror and the ſoundeſt part of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire could have had.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſe that the Empire had been in as good an harmony as it is at preſent, through the good Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on there is betwixt the Emperor and his Princes, and that <hi>France</hi> had nothing to do but with the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire alone; I maintain, that by only ſetting it ſelf in a poſture of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:44821:12"/>on the ſide of <hi>Germany,</hi> it might make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Maſter of a good pare of the <hi>Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſh Netherlands,</hi> if its Neighbour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> oppos'd not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to it, before the Emperor could remedy it. Beſides, that ſince the taking of <hi>Luxembourg,</hi> the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage is partly block'd up to the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> and all that they could do, wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to draw near to <hi>Burgundy,</hi> and to <hi>Alſatia,</hi> or form ſome conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Siege to draw the Arms of <hi>France</hi> that way; but as that would have hel'd the <hi>Germans</hi> long in hand, the <hi>French</hi> King would not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding do his buſineſs in <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if <hi>England</hi> had had on its Throne, as it has at preſent, a King well intention'd for the welfare of <hi>Europe,</hi> and the particular good of his own People, he might alone ſtop the <hi>French</hi> King in the appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion he has of landing Men on his Coaſts in his own Kingdom; and this truth is ſo certain, that <hi>Lewis</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:44821:12"/>the XIV. as powerful as he has been, as high as he would ſeem to be, has never undertaken any thing that way, but after he had conſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Kings of <hi>England</hi> then Reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and even <hi>Cromwell</hi> himſelf, while he uſurped the Government of the three Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>Thus we have ſeen that this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch before getting into <hi>Flanders,</hi> had ſweetned the Court of <hi>England</hi> by the means of his Honey; he taught them to ſpeak <hi>French,</hi> and to like whatever he did undertake, and quietly to let him ſo faſt advance, that at laſt it had no longer been in the power of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to drive him back. I know that <hi>France</hi> alone knows how much this has coſt it; but what matters at what rate, ſo one obtains ones Deſires. Thus the moſt Chriſtian King having diſpos'd <hi>England</hi> on that ſide, and having ſtrength e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, as doubtleſs he has, to ſet a conſiderable Army on foot on the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:44821:13"/>ſide of <hi>Germany,</hi> (beſides that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Flanders,</hi>) that he is in a condi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> to hazard a Battle with the Imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rialiſts and their Allies, if theſe la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> had the ill fortune to be beaten, a that may happen, the Succeſs bein<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> various, it is certain, That then th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Germans</hi> would have much to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to rally again into any Body tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were capable to do any advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous Exploit that Campaign fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the good of <hi>Flanders;</hi> there being nothing that waſtes more th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Troops that are compos'd of diver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Members, and under divers Chiefs than the ill ſucceſs of a firſt Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paign: And there needs ſometime but one Ally to decline the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Intereſt (like the Pin of a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage,) to put all the reſt out of power to do any thing, and to break the beſt Deſigns which might have been form'd; and it would be in ſuch like occaſion, that the Pride of <hi>France</hi> would ſwell, and that the uſurping Torrent would over-run
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:44821:13"/>its bounds more than ever on the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> which would be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hope of Remedies, if they were to wait for ſuccour from <hi>Germany,</hi> as it may eaſily be judged, by what I have ſaid, and which might eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have happen'd, there being no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing impoſſible in it.</p>
            <p>Moreover, <hi>France</hi> which has moſt ſtrong Reaſons to be on its guard, and to always fear, has long ſince ſo well provided for its Frontier places on all ſides, that it will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of its Enemies almoſt a whole Campaign to carry one only of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny importance.</p>
            <p>Since <hi>France</hi> has left the way to <hi>Italy,</hi> the King is ſo fully perſuaded, that the Conqueſt of the ſeventeen United Provinces of the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> would facilitate him the ways to that of <hi>Europe,</hi> but particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of the Empire; that he has ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd himſelf wholly to it, and has always endeavoured to amuſe by illuſive Promiſes, part of thoſe very
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:44821:14"/>Provinces, while that he render'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> himſelf Maſter of the other part<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> under the Dominion of <hi>Spain,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving firſt lull'd <hi>England</hi> aſleep, <hi>France</hi> requiring only the favour to decide alone that Diſpute with <hi>Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. might accompliſh that firſt Deſign on the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands,</hi> there was a neceſſity that the States of the United Provinces, which had a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table intereſt in the preſervation of the Neighbouring Provinces under their lawful Prince, ſhould give their helping hand to their ruine, or at leaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhould look on that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch without moving, till he had come on their Frontiers: But there was but little likelihood of that; wherefore the <hi>French</hi> King foreſeeing well, that thoſe States would never fall in that Lethargy, nor would permit to have their hands ty'd up while a conceal'd Enemy approach'd them, and penn'd
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:44821:14"/>them up cloſe, taking from them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ittle by little, all thoſe Places which were to ſerve them as Bars, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t was for that very Reaſon, that that Monarch did on the ſudden alter his mind, and beholding ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Deſires, what he had long expected, a Catholick Prince on the Throne of <hi>England,</hi> who had for divers years been in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is Pay, allowing him conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erable Penſions when yet he was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and conſequently <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>id entirely poſſeſs and obſeade him: He made uſe of the ill Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the new King, in his Concerns with the States General, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o that it was no longer difficult <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or the <hi>French</hi> King, who waited <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut for that moment, to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>liſh his Project; thus thoſe two Kings, the one puſh'd on by his Ambition, the other by his ill In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lination, join'd together to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erminate the Seven United Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inces, under the fair and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:44821:15"/>pretence of Religion, and <hi>Extirpating of Hereſie,</hi> that t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> other Catholick Princes, who we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> concern'd in the Preſervation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the United Provinces, might ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> oppoſe themſelves to ſuch an ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Work, and ſo lull them aſlee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> If that buſineſs had ſucceeded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. he had, witho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſtriking one blow, render'd hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Maſter, all under one, of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands;</hi> and after tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> made uſe of all the Forces of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Kingdom, together with thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his Conqueſts, to enter into <hi>Ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> and directly March to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Empire, follow'd with an Arm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of more than an Hundred Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Men; what Prince of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Empire, or the Emperor himſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> could have diſputed the Buſine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> with him, or have put a ſtop <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his March?</p>
            <p>But for ſo great a Work, it wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> neceſſary to faſten <hi>England</hi> firm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to his Intereſts, and to pull dow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:44821:15"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he States of the United Provinces, which was the chiefeſt Buſineſs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not being likely, that Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aigns, who ſo well know their own Intereſt as do thoſe States, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hould permit <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dvance one Foot of Ground more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>han he is already, (being but too <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orwards;) all that Monarchs fair Promiſes, and his kind aſſurances of Friendſhip remaining without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffect, not being able to win them to be deceiv'd: And perceiving that his Credit was at an end in thoſe Provinces. that all the Propoſitions of the Count <hi>d'Avaux,</hi> his Ambaſſador, were ſuſpected, and that he was ſtill entertain'd with much Circumſpection, (as Lions are fed, ſtill pulling the hand back;) finding himſelf diſcover'd and cried down, not to loſe any more time to flatter and amuſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e ſaid States, being not able to accompliſh his ends that way, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſolv'd to ruine them at the ſame
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:44821:16"/>time that King <hi>James</hi> the II. go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> on the Throne; he knowing we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his Genius, was ſatisfied that there wanted nothing but a Golden Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to amuſe him; and to follow that itching deſire which tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Prince had to render himſelf Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Maſter over all his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, to alter the Laws and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Religion of it; and to feed hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> before hand with the hopes of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Spaniſh Indies,</hi> that he might n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> longer find himſelf oblig'd to Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble his Parliament, who ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prov'd not of his Proceeding, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of that great Alliance he had wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>France;</hi> which, under what ſhap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſoever it was repreſented to them did always appear hiddeous. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all that long Interval, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> till there were a fair occaſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> perform that great Deſign, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>French</hi> Emiſſaries did continuall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pour their cold Poiſon in the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Court, which was quaff'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in large Draughts by ſome of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:44821:16"/>Grandees, which they endeavour'd to Digeſt without noiſe, ſeeing that at the ſame time they thus un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-hand ſet forward their Maſters Intereſt; others who were not at ſuch a diſtance, provided them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with an Apple againſt draught, as did many others in all the Courts of Chriſtendom.</p>
            <p>It was in this contagious time, ſo infected with the <hi>French Lewis D'Ors,</hi> that <hi>Europe</hi> was to tremble, and that all honeſt people, that concern'd themſelves in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Cauſe of the good of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom, were to ſhake at the very ſight of that weight which was going to cruſh <hi>Europe</hi> to pieces, ſeeing that its general loſs had immediately follow'd that of the Seventeen United Provinces; the Emperor nor the King of <hi>Spain</hi> not being then able to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, nor put a ſtop to that Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent which had chang'd it ſelf into a Deluge; from which, not
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:44821:17"/>
               <hi>England</hi> it ſelf had been Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted in its time, if afterward it would not have danc'd to the <hi>French</hi> Flutes, and obey'd the Orders of its Ambitious Monarch I am willing to make uſe of theſe Terms, ſeeing that all thoſe that are Penſioners of <hi>France,</hi> are ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> but to Execute his Orders, and to Work to increaſe the Grandeu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. not to oppoſe his Intereſts, but on the contrary Sacrifice their Honour and their Lives to them, ſo oft as the Good and the Intereſt of <hi>France</hi> ſhould require it. If ever <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV had obtain'd his end, and had made himſelf Maſter of the Forces of the Seventeen Provinces, as he plotted it in his greedy Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, through the King of <hi>England's</hi> Means, there had then been no ways left for this laſt to retire though he ſhould perceive his Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, as <hi>Charles</hi> the II. had done and he muſt either by fair or fou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:44821:17"/>means have gone on with that he had begun, through a weak Complacency; and then the <hi>Moſt Chriſtian King</hi> had rais'd his Voice and Arm at the ſame time, and had ſpoken in Magiſterial Terms to all the Princes of <hi>Europe;</hi> neither had that of <hi>England</hi> been left for the laſt, but had been oblig'd to ſubmit to the ſame Fate with all the others, as a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward for all the good Services that he ſhould have render'd him: I once again repeat, that the Deſigns of <hi>France</hi> were not new; that long ſince, <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. had had them before him, even before that <hi>James</hi> the II. had got on the Throne, and during his Brother's Reign, he luckily made uſe of the Dutcheſs of <hi>Orlean</hi>'s Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement, who was Siſter to both the Kings, <hi>Charles</hi> and <hi>James.</hi> But the Firſt of them, who had continually before his Eyes the Tragical end of his Father, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:44821:18"/>who was ſtill very ſenſible <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſufferings and troubles of his Exile, had much to do to reſolve upon it; and the Apprehenſions which he had of his People did retain him, and hindred him from Aſſiſting <hi>France</hi> in all things as he was ſolicited to do; and he at laſt did abandon it, as we did ſee by the Peace which he had made with the States of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Provinces, and then he ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly did relinquiſh the Intereſts of his Ally, not to Prorogue his Parliament, who very plainly did forſee the danger in which the Nation was going to fall, had <hi>France</hi> continued its Progreſs as it had began in 1672. and the years following.</p>
            <p>After the Peace of <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> the Kings great Deſign againſt the United Provinces, remain'd as buried during the remnant of King <hi>Charles</hi> his Reign; but he ſoon rais'd it again, for at King
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:44821:18"/>
               <hi>James</hi>'s Aſcending the Throne, <hi>France</hi> gather'd new Vigour, and beholding there ſo good a Friend, with whom he was tied in Religion and Inclination; <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. fail'd not to ſtrike the Iron while it was hot, and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Three or Four Years of his Reign, the <hi>French</hi> Emiſſaries gave divers Aſſaults, and ſet all Hands to work; the <hi>French</hi> Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador <hi>Barillon,</hi> made great Largeſſes, to all thoſe whom he thought propper to do his Maſter Service; the <hi>Curtiſans</hi> taſted of the Cake as well as divers Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters at Court; thus all unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly did labour to perſwade <hi>James</hi> the II. ſo ſoon as he was King, to ſecond <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. in his Deſigns (divers not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them) there needed no great Perſwaſion to attain it, becauſe that Prince was already ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently inclin'd to it of himſelf, and at that time, of all Employs,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:44821:19"/>that of Meſſenger was the moſt neceſſary; there was nothing ſeen but ſuch kind of Perſons on the Road from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Paris,</hi> and from <hi>Paris</hi> to <hi>London,</hi> till the Treaty was finiſh'd; of which, the chief matter and knot of the Buſineſs, was the ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the United Provinces: All the Religious Orders, and above all, the Jeſuits, did take a great Intereſt in that Buſineſs, and already cried out, <hi>The Town was their own;</hi> there was a perpetual motion among them; the Ships that croſs'd the Seas on both Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, were throng'd with thoſe Zealots and Apoſtolick Poſtilions; thus were all things in motion for the Good of <hi>France,</hi> and for the Advancement of its Monarchs Deſigns, ſome through Intereſt, ſome through Zeal, and others through meer Ignorance: This Buſineſs thus built up with Lime and Stone, concluded and reſolv'd
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:44821:19"/>on betwixt the Two Kings, <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. the better to compaſs all things, was deſirous to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then himſelf towards the North, but having loſt the friendſhip of the <hi>Sweeds,</hi> for having fail'd in keeping thoſe Treaties which had formerly paſs'd between the Two Crowns; <hi>France</hi> having no Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of patching them up again, it took the Party of <hi>Denmark,</hi> though it was nothing near ſo advantageous to it as was the other: To render it capable of employing it on all occaſions, he ſent thither the Count of <hi>Roy,</hi> there to Command, with many Officers and Men, but after the Siege of <hi>Hambourg,</hi> that General being retir'd, the <hi>French</hi> Party did much diminiſh; beſides, <hi>France</hi> could not Unite it ſelf with that Crown, in ſo ſtreight an Alliance as it wiſh'd for; and that it were neceſſary, becauſe of thoſe Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures which <hi>Denmark</hi> was to keep
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:44821:20"/>with the United Provinces on the account of Trade, without which it cannot do well, neither can it turn it to ſo good an account with <hi>France,</hi> it having at home all that it could draw from thence; ſo that all that <hi>France</hi> can at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent draw from that Alliance, can but at the moſt come but to a Neutrality, provided the Emperor and his Allies will give their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. was reckoning upon that, when he aſſur'd <hi>James</hi> the Second that the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> would not diſturb, but on the contrary favour them, in caſe that the <hi>Swede</hi> ſhould join with their Enemies: It was on that Pillow <hi>Lewis le Grand</hi> did gently lull aſleep the King of <hi>England,</hi> together with an ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary ſhower of Gold, which was to drop from the <hi>Spaniſh Indies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how great ſoever a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption is at Court, there are
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:44821:20"/>ſtill ſome good; and the ſoundeſt part of the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> could not reliſh that ſtreight U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion which was betwixt their Prince and <hi>France,</hi> it clearly did ſee, that on its ſide the deſign was to Change the Religion, to Subvert the Laws, Eſtabliſh an Arbitrary Power, and a Deſpotick Government, which tended to the loſs of their Liberties and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, and to depend one Day on <hi>France,</hi> which gave them ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picion of every ſtep which the Ambaſſador <hi>Barillon,</hi> and the Queen did make in that reſpect; but their Zeal did ſo far tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port them, that at laſt the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the Lords, the Proteſtant Clergy open'd their Eyes, and thought of delivering themſelves, and with them all <hi>Europe,</hi> from thoſe ſhackles which were forging for them; and the Heavens granting the Petition of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom, and in particular of the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:44821:21"/>
               <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation, it ſent them a Deliverer, of whom Providence hath ſo miraculouſly ſeconded the Enterpriſe, ſo as to prevent them from falling under an hard Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, and under the Government of a ſuppos'd Prince, a Foundling, whoſe Father and Mother remain ſtill unknown, which was to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd to the Lawful Heirs of the Crown; ſuch a black and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of Supplanting, did oblige the Princeſs of <hi>Orange,</hi> as the next Heir to the Kingdom, to intreat the Prince her Husband, to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond the juſt Requeſt of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and of the moſt ſound part of the Kingdom. Thus the Prince, by an Admirable Conduct and a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Diſpenſation, did bring things about according to the Hearts deſire of the Nation, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out effuſion of Blood, and ſet Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion in its due and right Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel, which was to have been
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:44821:21"/>interrupted by the means of that ſuppos'd Child; for the Princeſs having been Crown'd Queen by Succeſſion, and the Prince King by Acknowledgment, after the Throne had been declar'd Vacant through King <hi>James</hi> the Il's Deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; it happen'd very luckily for the Deliverance of <hi>Europe,</hi> which I ſhall prove in what follows, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Subject of this ſmall Book.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, I lay down for an indiſputable Truth, That if <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. and <hi>James</hi> the II. had compaſs'd their Deſigns and Ends, the United Provinces had been entirely loſt, through the breaking down of their Banks; for that way did he deſign to begin, to take away all means from the Inhabitants of ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering from that Diſſolution in which he deſign'd to Reduce them, after they had made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Maſters of the <hi>Spaniſh Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlands;</hi> after which, I cannot
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:44821:22"/>perceive how <hi>Europe</hi> could have prevented falling under the Yoak of the <hi>French</hi> Dominion, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had the King of <hi>England</hi> for Second, and Invading the 17 United Provinces, and rendring Tributary in imitation of the Grand Seignior, the moſt remote of thoſe Provinces, which he could not conveniently Govern.</p>
            <p>I have already given to obſerve, that the Empire alone could not hinder him, by reaſon of the great number of heads, all of different and diſtinct Intereſts, of thoſe Princes that Compoſe it: On the other hand, <hi>Spain</hi> being not in a Condition to raiſe Forces ſufficient to oppoſe it, nor all of them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether capable to reſiſt the rapid motion with which <hi>France</hi> would invade them after its Firſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts.</p>
            <p>For to repreſent to us what <hi>France</hi> can do, and what it has been able to do in all times, we
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:44821:22"/>need but to frame to our ſelves a right Idea of things, from <hi>Francis</hi> the Firſt, to <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, we ſhall eaſily judge that it has alwaies been dreaded; this laſt was both Emperor and King of <hi>Spain</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; he was Maſter of the 17 United Provinces, while they were entire, he had <hi>Burgundy</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> County, as well as <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatia;</hi> he had an abſolute power over the Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> and of <hi>Italy.</hi> This Monarch was with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out diſpute, one of the Greateſt Princes, not only of his Time, but of his Age; a Great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander, undaunted in all his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſes, daring Perils and Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, in which he had frequently been, and add to all that his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Valour, a good Head-Piece, and fit for Counſel, encouraging his Armies by his Preſence, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving under him the moſt Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rienc'd Captains, and the beſt Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals of his Time, and ſuch Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:44821:23"/>that had been tried in all parts of <hi>Germany, Italy,</hi> and in the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> beſides Fleets on the Mediterranian, and on the Ocean.</p>
            <p>With all thoſe Forces, his Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and his Treaſures, though he had to do but with <hi>Francis</hi> the Firſt, who alone was his Capital Enemy, and who was nothing near ſo powerful as his Succeſſors have been (and as <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIVth. is at this time, or at leaſt as he has been of late years,) having no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Revenue, but about thirty, or thirty five <hi>French</hi> Millions, whereas this preſent has four times as much.</p>
            <p>Mean time, with all this diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of Forces and of Wealth, this Emperor durſt not attack him, 'till firſt he had joyn'd himſelf with <hi>Henry</hi> the VIIIth of <hi>England,</hi> and with the moſt conſiderable Princes of <hi>Italy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this we find that even from
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:44821:23"/>that time the Emperoor did highly conſider the Kings o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>England,</hi> and that if <hi>Francis</hi> the Firſt, King of <hi>France,</hi> had firſt ſecur'd <hi>Henry</hi> the VIIIth's Alliance, <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth had not dar'd to attack him; and with all the advantages that the Emperor had of his ſide, <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt ſtood out againſt him, and without the Misfortune that befell him at the Seige of <hi>Pavia,</hi> where he was made Priſoner, he had given work enough to his Enemy.</p>
            <p>I paſs from <hi>Francis</hi> the Firſt to <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIVth, much more powerful in Forces, in Treaſures, and in Demains, than his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors, ſeconded, as he believ'd by a ſtrict alliance with <hi>England,</hi> having no more to manage nor to fear from the United Provinces, I leave to gueſs what he had, and might have done, and how far he had puſh'd on his Ambition; I maintain that then, the Pope with
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:44821:24"/>all <hi>Italy,</hi> the Emperor with the whole Empire, and <hi>Spain</hi> with all the Riches of the <hi>Indies,</hi> had not been of power to hinder him from making himſelf Maſter of all <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is but <hi>England</hi> alone then that is Capable to make the moſt Chriſtian King alter his Deſigns; and that could not happen, but by ſuch a lucky Cataſtrophe, and ſo unexpected as that which has lately happen'd there, under the Reign of <hi>William</hi> the IIId. For there was requir'd to be Sitting on the Throne, in order to ſuch a Change, a Diſintereſted Prince, Zealous of the Glory of God, and the good of <hi>Chriſtendom:</hi> Jealous of the Uſurpation which <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIVth had made in <hi>Europe,</hi> Incorruptible, Magnanimous, a Man of Counſel and Execution, underſtanding well his own Intereſt, and who had been highly provok'd by <hi>France;</hi> that he might not hearken to any
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:44821:24"/>accommodation, nor yield any thing, to the prejudice of his Allies. This is what we find en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely in that Prince who has newly Aſcended the <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Throne; wherefore ſo ſoon as this Heroe had paſs'd over into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and that a happy Succeſs had ſeconded his Great Deſigns; we have ſeen <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIVth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come motionleſs on the ſudden, as formerly did <hi>Atlas,</hi> at the ſight of the <hi>Meduſa</hi>'s head, which was ſhew'd him by that Generous <hi>Perſeus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Foundation on which the <hi>French</hi> King had built his Grand Deſign, (the ſtrict Alliance which he had with <hi>James</hi> the Second) having once given way, all the reſt of the Fabrick is fallen to the ground, and his Caſtles in the Air have gone into Smoak, having no hopes to take any Meaſures in his Deſigns with this his preſent <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanick</hi> Majeſty, who, to cut off
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:44821:25"/>all his Hopes, and ſtop all his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, has driven out of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> all the <hi>French</hi> Emiſſaries, reſolv'd never to hearken any more to them, in the Deſign he has to reſtore the quiet and tranquility of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> and to maintain <hi>Europe</hi> in that Deliverance which He has lately procur'd to it, by his only Elevation to the Throne. I prove my Axiome by that which follows; When a Town is Beſieg'd, and that at the approach of its De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverer, its Enemies abandon it, and their Deſigns miſcarry, they retire, and though the Heroe which has caus'd its deliverance, be not yet enter'd that Place, it is publiſh'd abroad that the Place is Reliev'd, as really it is. So <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIVth having a Deſign of Conquering <hi>Europe,</hi> to Depoſe the Lawful Soveraigns thereof, and to Sacrifice all <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> to his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, as it is no longer doubted; it being a Truth but too well
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:44821:25"/>averr'd and known. That Uſurper has no ſooner ſeen <hi>William</hi> the IIId Proclaim'd King, but that he has abandon'd his Enterpriſe, and chang'd his Deſign; and in lieu of deſtroying the Powers of <hi>Europe,</hi> has had no other thoughts but of preſerving himſelf, and his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. I joyn to the coming of <hi>William</hi> the IIId to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> the ſtrict Alliance there is between his Majeſty of Great <hi>Brittain,</hi> and the States of the United Provinces, as alſo the Union of the Emperor with all the Princes of the Empire.</p>
            <p>I confeſs, that it has been a great Buſineſs to have freed <hi>Europe</hi> from the danger which threatned it, to have diſpers'd in a Moment all the great and pernicious Deſigns of an Ambitious Prince, that on all occaſions made no ſcruple to break his Faith when that Crime agreed with his Ambition and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, who, notwithſtanding his
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:44821:26"/>Word given to the Contrary, back'd with his Oath, has neither ſpar'd the blood nor the ruine of ſo many Thouſands of Chriſtians, in the bare Opinion, that he ought to do it for his Intereſt's ſake, and to weaken his Enemies; having not ſpar'd even his own Subjects. And if we return to the Primary Cauſe, we cannot but believe, that the Heavens wearied with ſo much In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice, with ſo much Cruelty, and enormous Crimes, and with ſo much blood-ſhed, which Cries for Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, has at laſt rais'd <hi>William</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> on the Throne, and ſuggeſted a good Union amongſt the Princes of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> to ſtop the Barbarous Courſe of <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIVth.</p>
            <p>But it is not enough to have reduc'd the Lyon that Sack'd <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> to get into his Den, his Claw muſt be pair'd alſo, and his Teeth pull'd out, that hereafter he may do
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:44821:26"/>no more harm, and that his Power may be limited, that he may no longer Deſolate our Countries, that he devour no more the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, and that the moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, Oppreſs no more the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIVth's Policy and Intereſt in the Condition he is at preſent reduc'd, is to gain time, to ſee whether any Change would not happen in <hi>England,</hi> nor no Conteſtation in <hi>Germany;</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore he offers in all places he can Neutrality, that he might find <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thoſe Princes that ſhould not declare themſelves ſome Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ors, or to ſpeak more properly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>terceſſors near the Emperor and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e King of <hi>England,</hi> as well as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ear the United Provinces, in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r he is of a total downfall, if <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ngland,</hi> and the Empire continue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they have began, and as it is to believ'd they will do, according <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all appearance, if they love <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eir quiet, their preſervation, and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:44821:27"/>their own Intereſts, as well as the good of their People.</p>
            <p>I confeſs that much has been done, eſpecially by the King o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>England,</hi> to have deliver'd <hi>Europ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> at preſent without drawing his Sword, but the future muſt be thought on, and the means mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> be taken from <hi>France,</hi> of any more threatning <hi>Europe,</hi> to ſet it in right Ballance with the Houſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Auſtria,</hi> or at leaſt in a Conditio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of having need of its Allies, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not put an end to this preſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> War which is kindling in all places 'till that be perform'd.</p>
            <p>To ſucceed the better in it, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to animate the more all the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Europe,</hi> they ought to ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> up what <hi>France</hi> has Uſurped from them, the dammage they hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> receiv'd by it, and that whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they may receive hereafter; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> never lay down their Arms, 'ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they all have had full ſatisfaction for the more it ſhall be fore'd t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:44821:27"/>reſtore, the more will its Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign be weakned.</p>
            <p>I ſet in the firſt Rank the Pope, who by all the Catholicks is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd as the head of the Church, Chriſt's Vicar on Ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, St. <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi>'s Succeſſor, the Common Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of all Chriſtians, the Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer of Celeſtial Graces, and who being conſider'd as ſuch, ought to be fear'd, reſpected, rever'd, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour'd and obey'd; as to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itual, (laying aſide the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt which is among the Catholicks themſelves concerning the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral) and not withſtanding that <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIVth names himſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Eldeſt Son of the Church, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he moſt devout Son of the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaign Pontiſ, what Mortification has not the good Father receiv'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rom him, ſince his coming to the Pontificate, either in his own Perſon, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r in that of his Legates, even <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon the dead Corps of one of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem. The extinction of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galia</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:44821:28"/>in <hi>France,</hi> is alſo a great grie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the Holy See, as well as th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> violence us'd againſt divers Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents, for having addreſs'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Pope, and taking advice of his Holineſs. The changing of divers Abbies into Commad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries by the King's own and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per motion, is alſo a Contemp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which he has aggravated by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> forbiddance he has made to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Biſhops not to Conſult the Hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> See, even in Caſes of Conſcienc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and in ſuch buſineſſes as whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> concern Religion: but the mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſenſible of all, was that blow gi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ven to the Pope's Authority, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Year 1682. by the Clergy A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled at the King's Command that being with the Infallibilit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the fineſt Flowers of the Trip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Crown. The Inſolent Diſcour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> held in a Plea by Monſieur <hi>Tal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> by which he accus'd Pope <hi>Innocen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the XIth (the moſt worthy tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> has for divers years been ſea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:44821:28"/>in St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Chair) of being a Schiſmatick, and a Supporter of Hereticks. And this, for not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving receiv'd Monſiour <hi>Lavardin</hi> as Ambaſſa for at <hi>Rome,</hi> who made his Entry into that City in ſuch an offenſive and proud manner, that no Ambaſſadours of Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience durſt ever have done the like; having caus'd himſelf to be accompany'd by a ſmall Army rather than a Retinue, as if he would have Beſieg'd the <hi>Vatican.</hi> And though this Marqueſs is at full Liberty at <hi>Rome,</hi> the Nuncio <hi>Ranucci</hi> is detain'd in a place call'd St. <hi>Lazarus,</hi> for fear he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire from <hi>Paris incognito.</hi> Finally, the unjuſt ſeizure of the City and County of <hi>Avignon,</hi> threatning beſides all this, to ſend ſome Troops into the Eccleſiaſtick State, to oblige the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e to r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>e the Bull for the abolition of Quarters, and that for hsi Confirmation of Prince <hi>Joſeph Clement</hi> of <hi>Bavaria</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:44821:29"/>to the Archbiſhoprick of <hi>Cologne</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After ſo much inſulting which the Pope had receiv'd, of which one might make a whole Volum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> either in his own Perſon, his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, or in the Perſon of his Legates, the Pope has judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly done, to ſhew his Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to relinquiſh any of his Rights, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> maintain the Rank which he ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the Church, and in the World, by that Spiritual and Tempora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Power, which God has put into his Hands, and in having till now ſo generouſly and juſtly oppos'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to all the <hi>French</hi> Violences, by which he has acquir'd a Glory which ſhall laſt as long as the World, amongſt all Parties<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and his Memory will be Rever'd even after his Death: He ought to go on in thoſe right Paths which he has begun, and as Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Father, Exhort all Catholick Princes, to put themſelves in a
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:44821:29"/>Condition to abate the Pride of the <hi>French</hi> King, as a means to bring him into a way of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. To this purpoſe, the Pope ought with all his Power to Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit the Catholick Princes, that he may co-operate in ſo good a Work, as his Holineſs has done to the Empire againſt the Turks; and to ſolicite the <hi>Switz-Cantons,</hi> of the ſame Religion, by his Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates, to Join themſelves to the Emperor and Empire, to confirm that Deliverance which <hi>Europe</hi> begins to enjoy: Thus the Pope being reſtor'd to his former Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, Veneration, and Authority, let the King, his moſt devout Son, make him ſome Reparations and Attonements, for thoſe Faults he has committed, and be ſo humbled, that for the future he may be Wiſer, and out of Power of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the like again, nor of Inſult<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over the Popes and Soveraign Pontifs of the Catholick Church;
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:44821:30"/>and in caſe the Pope found no amendment in that King, nor no likelihood of bringing him back to his Duty, he ought, while he is buſie in a War, to lance forth his Excommunications againſt him, and to give his Kingdoms over to the Spoil of his Enemies; the male-contented Eccleſiaſticks, with which his Kingdom is fill'd, will reduce him by Reaſon, and will make him repent having ever meddled with the Rights of the Church.</p>
            <p>The Emperor and the Princes of the Empire, have more Reaſon than all the other Powers of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> to keep the <hi>French</hi> King in ſuch a condition, that he may no more annoy them, nor aſpire to the Imperial Crown. <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. has a long time endeavour'd to turn the Empire into the <hi>French</hi> Family, as in the time of <hi>Charle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main,</hi> it being a great ſtep for him to riſe to that of all <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope;</hi>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:44821:30"/>that is the Reaſon why, ſince <hi>Francis</hi> the Firſt, the <hi>French</hi> Kings have always croſs'd the Emperors Elections. But <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great could find no way to that Conqueſt, but by the total Ruine of the United Provinces, to which he could not attain, but by the aſſiſtance of <hi>England;</hi> thus his Imperial Majeſty, and all the Princes of the Empire, being fully ſatisfied of this Truth, and that nothing but that Revolution which has lately happen'd on the <hi>Brittiſh</hi> Throne, could cauſe the raſh Deſigns of the <hi>French</hi> King to Miſcarry. The Emperor ought no longer to r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in in ſuſpence, nor put off to another time, thoſe Advan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s which t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Heavens preſent to him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this time, to recover all tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>France</hi> has Uſurp'd from him.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe, his Imperial Majeſty ſhould begin by a Truce, which he ought, without
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:44821:31"/>delay, to conclude with the Port, ſeeing that they offer it on very honourable and advantageous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions; and let the Emperor hold as ſuſpicious Perſons, all ſuch as ſhall Adviſe him to the contrary they are Perſons that ſin either through Ignorance, or Malice who underſtand not the true Intereſts of the Empire, or too much thoſe of <hi>France;</hi> he is not to doubt, but that all the Princes of the Empire will concur to the ſame Deſign, of abaſing the Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the <hi>French</hi> Monarch, of which there are but very few Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in the Empire that have not great cauſe of complaint, and juſt pretenſions to frame, and perhaps, more to pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>end to than ever to recover again, if <hi>France</hi> be not kept in a condition of never of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending them more; of domineer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any longer, nor of boaſting any more that it can give Peace to <hi>Europe</hi> when ever it pleaſes.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:44821:31"/>This laſt War, by the rupture of a Truce, which the <hi>French</hi> King had ſought after, with ſo much earneſtneſs, becauſe it confirm'd <hi>Luxemburg</hi> to him, and a part of <hi>Flanders</hi> during Twenty Years, and which he has infring'd with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Cauſe, than his deſire to come to the Aſſiſtance of the Grand Seignior, who was going to ruine, by the vaſt Conqueſts which the Emperor made on that Inſidel: His <hi>Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty,</hi> was going hand over head to his Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, finding himſelf ſupported with a cloſe Alliance with <hi>James</hi> the II. formerly King of <hi>Great Britain;</hi> this Rupture has given new pretenſions of War to all the Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> by the moſt barbarous and inhum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e proceedings which the <hi>Fren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Troops have done there; and I doubt much, whether a juſt P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel could be drawn from the Cruelties and Deſolations that this
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:44821:32"/>King has caus'd to be committed in the Palatinate, with thoſe that the Grand Seignior has made in <hi>Hungary;</hi> and though this laſt place has been for a long time the Seat of War, yet at the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat of the Infidels, they have not committed any thing near the like Extortions, nor us'd the ſame violence, that the <hi>French</hi> have done in thoſe places that they have abandon'd in the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and in the Country of <hi>Juliers,</hi> and of <hi>Cologne;</hi> and if there were no other cauſe but this, though there are but too many more, there would need, in my Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, nothing but the ſad ſpectacle of the <hi>French</hi> barbarouſneſs, to ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate all the Princes and Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of <hi>Europe,</hi> to a good and firm Union with the Emperor, which will be the only means to preſerve themſelves, and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent <hi>France</hi> from doing the like hereafter.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:44821:32"/>
            <p>Though <hi>France</hi> is brought low, through the oppoſition of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in all its Deſigns, yet has it not forgot its ancient Maxims; which have formerly ſucceeded ſo well; it will not ſail to put into practice all the ways ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable to corrupt ſome Member of the Empire, and to break that Chain of Unity there is amongſt them, to endeavour thereby, to put a ſtop to the Succeſs of their Arms, as it frequently happens, that a broken or rotten Pin, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders a whole Carriage, and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders its March.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>France's</hi> Crafts and Deceits be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing already ſo well fore-known, it is requiſite that the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> ſhould provide againſt that plague of Corruption, which has ſo freequently infected divers Courts of Chriſtendom; divers are to expect, that not only Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents will be offer'd to them, as well as Penſions, but equivalents alſo
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:44821:33"/>to their Pretenſions, only to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main Neuter: But the Example of the Archbiſhop of <hi>Mentz</hi> is yet ſo freſh before our Eyes, that it ought to be a fair Mirror for the Princes of the Empire, to Repreſent to them to the Life, the Character of <hi>France,</hi> and of its Soveraign, which all that proceeding repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents in Lively Colours, with the breaches of Faith of that Prince, even to thoſe that Side with him. If ever any Soveraign did Act againſt his true Intereſt, and that of the whole Empire, it was that Prelate; but then again, never was Prince worſe rewarded, nor had greater cauſe to repent of his Fault, by the ill uſage he has ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in his Eſtate; which had reach'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to his Perſon alſo, if he had no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhelter'd himſelf from the Threat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the <hi>French</hi> Envoy.</p>
            <p>But he is not the only Living and Speaking Example; the whol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Series of time that has paſs'd ſince
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:44821:33"/>the Peace of the <hi>Pireneans,</hi> is but a continued Thread of the falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of <hi>France.</hi> So, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall catch at the Golden Bait which the King lays for them, will have time to Repent themſelves, as the Elector of <hi>Mentz</hi> has done, and divers others, who have fair'd no better.</p>
            <p>But if, by a Fatal Chance, it ſhould ſo happen, that ſome Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Empire were ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advis'd, as to be Corrupted by <hi>France,</hi> and ſeparated from that Union which is its true Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, though it is not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected now that thoſe Princes are ſo well enlightned; that Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ought to be conſider'd as a rotten Member, Diſcarded, and Treated as an Enemy, though he would remain Neuter, on this ground drawn from the Holy Goſpel, <hi>Qui non eſt pro nobis eſt contra nos.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of Truth the Union of the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:44821:34"/>Empire is of great Importance, and I muſt confeſs, that all its United Forces may be very pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful, but they would be much more, if the Emperor could re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to grant a Peace to the Grand Seignior; that ſo having no longer any thing to fear from that Part, his Imperial Majeſty may have his Hands at liberty againſt the Second, which has been much more formidable and more dangerous than the Firſt, and conſequently cauſe all his Forces to Advance towards the <hi>Rhine,</hi> which would produce Two Effects; the one, that ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Armies would increaſe that Terror in which <hi>France</hi> is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready. Secondly, it would by that means much better maintain that Union which is already in <hi>Europe,</hi> with their Allies.</p>
            <p>Beſides, it is a general Rule, which the Emperor ought always to obſerve; never to have Two
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:44821:34"/>Wars to maintain at the ſame time, eſpecially when he can a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void one of them, as it is in his power to do at this preſent, with great Advantage and Glory.</p>
            <p>It is not to be doubted, but that the <hi>French</hi> King does highly dread ſuch a Truce; that he will openly and moſt powerfully Act with the Turk, and the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and that he will have his Emiſſaries, conceal'd, at the Court of <hi>Vienna,</hi> that will labour un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-hand, and on deceitful Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to prevent the Imperial Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil from concluding any thing with the Turks Envoy, at this preſent at <hi>Vienna.</hi> To be ſure, he will neither ſpare Money nor Religion to attain his end therein.</p>
            <p>To the Grand Seignior, he Promiſes to enter into <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> with a Powerful Army, to Ranſack there, as he has done al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, thereby to draw the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors Forces on that ſide, and
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:44821:35"/>give the Great Turk the means and leaſure to breathe again, and to Aſſemble new Forces to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to regain what he has loſt.</p>
            <p>To <hi>Teckeley,</hi> and the Princes of <hi>Tranſilvania, Walachia,</hi> and <hi>Moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>davia,</hi> without enquiring of what Religion they are, he aſſures con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Sums to continue the War begun; he has frequenly ſent ſome to the Firſt, and if the others would break off with the Emperor, and join with the Grand Seignior, he would furniſh them wherewith to Pay their Forces.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Poland,</hi> that will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form enough for <hi>France,</hi> if its King will but remain quiet, and not at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt any thing, as he has done ſince the two laſt Campaigns, and prevent by great pretenſions the Concluſion of a Truce with the Port. <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIVth has Springs that are ſufficiently ſtrong to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain him, and to obtain what he
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:44821:35"/>pleaſes of that Crown, perſwading it that it is not ſuitable to her In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, to have the Emperor proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſo much, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the Court of <hi>Vienna,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> Emiſſaries Labour through indirect means, to perſwade the Emperor's Councellors, that his Imperial Majeſty may with eaſe maintain the War againſt the <hi>Turk</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> and that it concerns his Glory not to ſlacken in ſo fair a Courſe, that he ought to go and plant the Croſs of Chriſt on the very Battlements of the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raglio</hi> at <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> but ſuch pretences are at great diſtance from their Maſters thoughts, for it is very certain, that the <hi>French</hi> King had rather ſee once more the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent on St. <hi>Stephen</hi>'s Church at <hi>Vienna,</hi> than the Croſs on St. <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia</hi> at <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIVth at this time, is like to a Man in great extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of danger, that is ready to ſink,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:44821:36"/>he makes Vows, and promiſes all things, to get out again, and takes hold of all that comes in his way, to keep himſelf ſome moments lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger above water. Thus this Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch has turn'd himſelf all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ways to find out a Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor that would aſſiſt him to get our of the danger he is in. He has addreſs'd himſelf to the Elector of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> and to the Pope; but at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, knowing of no better ſhift, and finding that all the Chriſtian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces do abandon him, he has ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd himſelf to the <hi>Turk.</hi> And finding that no Chriſtians will any longer confide in him, be covers himſelf with a falſe M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sk of Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poceiſie; he demonſtrates to the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> that the Roman Catholick Religion is in danger, and that it periſhes with him, that it has been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hrough his Care and Zeal ſo many Converſions have been made in his Kingdom, and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:44821:36"/>that he was ready to have done as much in <hi>England,</hi> if there had not been a League made againſt him. But with all theſe ſugar'd words, he at the ſame time Leagues himſelf with the Enemy of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom, at that very time he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and puts all to the Fire and Sword, he offers to the Grand Seignior to joyn him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with him on the defenſive part, and not to lay down his Arms, 'till the Sultan has recover'd <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary.</hi> At the ſame time he offers to the Pope, that if the Emperor will agree with him, he will lend him forty Gallies to aid him to Conquer <hi>Conſtantinople;</hi> and offers to Re-eſtabliſh King <hi>James</hi> in his Kingdoms, provided that the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror and the Empire will Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude a Peace with him. All theſe are fair Flowers that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal a Serpent under them, who will certainly ſting the hand of him that will but touch them.</p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:44821:37"/>
            <p>Theſe are the <hi>French</hi> King's De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits, which he has Inherited from <hi>Mazarine,</hi> to trye whether by ſuch fair Offers he might not break the Union of the Empire.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Flanders,</hi> the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> the Countries of <hi>Juliers,</hi> and of <hi>Ments, Treves</hi> and <hi>Colen,</hi> remain unrepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chable Teſtimonies of his Breaches of Faith, and of his Hypocriſie; he having nothing leſs in his thoughts than the Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. For thoſe Offers which his Ambaſſador <hi>Guichardin</hi> has made to the <hi>Port,</hi> ought once for all, to undeceive all Chriſtendom of that Catholick Faith of which he makes ſo great a ſhew.</p>
            <p>But not to reſt any longer on the Illuſions and Deceitful Offer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>France,</hi> which ought to be ſuſpicious to all the Princes of <hi>Europe.</hi> I ſay that the Emperor and the Empire ought not to ſtop in the very beginning of ſo fair an Opportunity which <hi>England</hi>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:44821:37"/>offers them, nor lay down their Arms, 'till they have recover'd <hi>Burgundy,</hi> the <hi>French County, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſace,</hi> but particulary <hi>Strasbourg, Philip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>burg, Fribourg, Briſack,</hi> and all that <hi>France</hi> has Uſurp'd on that ſide of <hi>Europe.</hi> Moreover, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeated the Electors <hi>Palatine,</hi> of <hi>Mentz, Treves</hi> and <hi>Colen,</hi> in their Territories and Rights, with an entire reparation of all thoſe Wrongs and Damages which he has done them by his Forces and Incendiaries Reſign Cardinal <hi>Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtenberg</hi> into the hands of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, or of the Pope, to anſwer to thoſe things that ſhall be alledg'd againſt him, and that he is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready accus'd of.</p>
            <p>But that which is moſt juſt and neceſſary, is to reſtore the Duke of <hi>Lorain</hi> to his Dukedom, which ought to be reſtituted in the ſame Condition that it was in the time of his Predeceſſors. Policy requires that this Dukedom ſhould be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:44821:38"/>from <hi>France,</hi> becauſe that would be a means to weaken <hi>France.</hi> It would be to fix a Thorn in its foot, thus to Re-eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh the Succeſſor of the Ancient Soveraigns, to ſupport and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold it, that it might no longer be liable to fall under the Forces of <hi>France,</hi> nor to acquieſce to any Treaty prejudiciable to it, nor ſo much as to have any great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication with them, becauſe that the Duke of <hi>Lorain</hi> being once reſtor'd to his Eſtates, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he, nor his Suceſſors ought nevermore to truſt to the <hi>French</hi> Kings; but ought daily to ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their Eyes, with what perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deouſneſs his Predeceſſor has been Treated.</p>
            <p>Thoſe Great Victories which that Prince has gain'd with ſuch great Succeſs and Glory over the <hi>Turks,</hi> the re-union of <hi>Hungary</hi> to the Empire, which is due to his ſole Valour, does well deſerve
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:44821:38"/>that all Chriſtian Princes ſhould Conſerve themſelves for this Great Heroe; Joyn to that the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which his Imperial Majeſty has with that Duke, by his Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iage with the Queen of <hi>Poland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not to be doubted, but that <hi>William</hi> the IIId. King of Great <hi>Brittain,</hi> will Contribute with all his Power to ſo Juſt and Laudable an Enterpriſe, even ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for the quiet of <hi>Europe;</hi> and that his Britanick Majeſty will impoſe it as a Law on Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to bring it about, if he once undertakes it. But to Compaſs this with more eaſe, The Duke of <hi>Lorain</hi> ought before all things elſe to propoſe a Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in all his Dominion, and free Exerciſe to all Proteſtants, in all the Cities and Borroughs where there are any. That will be a means to draw on his ſide, the Aſſiſtance of all thoſe of that Religion, as well as that of the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:44821:39"/>Allies, and of their Subjects, in laying aſide the Counſels of a Company of Monks, which conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually beat over and over in divers Catholick Princes Ears, to make them act the contrary, and to puſh them forward to a Perſecution, which will ever prove hurtful to their Perſons and Sates.</p>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Lorrain</hi> ought not to let ſlip ſo fair and ſo favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble an occaſion, which perhaps will never offer it ſelf again in all his Life time, nor that of his Succeſſors; his Intereſt and that of his Family obliges him to embrace it, and to ſoliciate the King of <hi>England</hi> as well as the Emperor; and thoſe Princes who Compoſe the Diet of <hi>Ratisbone,</hi> who are already inclin'd to it, by the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Proceedings of the <hi>French,</hi> they, doubtleſs, will not fall to eſpouſe the Intereſt of that Prince, in conſideration of thoſe Services which he has render'd to
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:44821:39"/>Chriſtendom; and to labour in his Re-eſtabliſhment, as well as in that of others, the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that <hi>Lorrain</hi> being in that Duke's Hands, will ſerve as a Bar to the Empire; but as I have already ſaid, that Prince ought to Labour particularly to bring the Emperor and his Council to grant a Truce to the Grand Seignior; without which, I cannot ſee his own Concerns can have any good Succeſs. This he ought to conſider, before ſending back the Turks Envoy, leſt he ſhould ſlip the Occaſion; for after that every one will take new Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures.</p>
            <p>The Emperor never had, nor never will have a fairer Occaſion to entirely Maſter <hi>France,</hi> than that which at this preſent he is furniſhed with, by the coming of <hi>William</hi> the III. to the Crown of <hi>England;</hi> which ſeems as if God had produc'd that Effect, during
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:44821:40"/>the time of that great Union of the Princes of the Empire, to give an Opportunity to his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Majeſty to Subdue <hi>France;</hi> being thereunto excited by the ill Uſage they have all receiv'd from the <hi>French</hi> King, and the barbarous Proceeding which he has us'd of late in <hi>Germany,</hi> which has been but a continuation of thoſe Cruelties which his Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons have exercis'd in his own Kingdom; which has not only alienated from him the Hearts of his Subjects, but has ſtruck an Horror in all Chriſtendom; he has depriv'd the <hi>Moſt Chriſtian King</hi> of all his Alliances, and has reduc'd him, to ſee himſelf oblig'd to have recourſe to the Swor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Enemy of Chriſtianity, the Turk</p>
            <p>All theſe Advantages are found in this preſent juncture; more over, <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. the bor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Enemy to the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> is now at Wars with all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:44821:40"/>If his Imperial Majeſty takes not advantage of thoſe Conveniences which the Heavens ſeem to preſent him with, he ought not to expect any Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgments from <hi>France</hi> for it, nor that the King will think he hath done him a kindneſs in ſparing him; for as he has the gift of Uſurpation by Inheritance, if he can but raiſe himſelf up again from that Mortal Wound he has receiv'd, he will come, as did the Grand Viſier, (after he has, if he can, diſunited and ruin'd the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire) and Encamp his Army be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Vienna.</hi> That Itch has held him a long time, and <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. has Inherited it from his Predeceſſors; for ſince the Death of <hi>Ferdinando</hi> the III. thoſe Kings that have Reign'd in <hi>France,</hi> have always endeavour'd to poſſeſs the place of <hi>Charlemain,</hi> and in 1683. His <hi>Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty,</hi> who was very well Inſtructed of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet</hi>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:44821:41"/>the IV's Deſigns, and who had inſtigated <hi>Teckeley</hi> to Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, did think then, that he had obtain'd his Hearts Deſires, and that he had got the Wind of the Emperor, for he thought it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible but that <hi>Vienna</hi> ſhould fall under the Power of the Grand Viſier's Forces. The King had Forty Thouſand Men ready on the Borders of <hi>Germany,</hi> in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to put himſelf at the Head of them, and to enter into the Empire, to have himſelf Proclaim'd Emperor, as the ancient <hi>Romans</hi> did, at the Head of his Army. His pretence had been, That his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Majeſty, not being in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to preſerve Chriſtendom, he was come to ſupply his Place; and as the Deliverer of <hi>Europe,</hi> free it from the Oppreſſion of the Infidels, though he himſelf had Invited them in, and had deſign'd to put it in Irons. To make good the Truth of what I alledge, I
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:44821:41"/>muſt ſay, that this Monarch, who thought himſelf aſſur'd of the taking of the City <hi>Vienna</hi> by the Turks, and himſelf, conſequently, of the Imperial Crown, had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready caus'd the Imperial Eagle to be plac'd over his Effigy, in his own Coin, publickly declaring before his whole Court, <hi>That the Empire had remain'd already long enough in the Houſe of</hi> Auſtria, <hi>and that it was high time it ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn into his Family.</hi> The <hi>French</hi> Mercenary Pens, and the <hi>French</hi> Flatterers, had already ſet forth di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Pieces in that Kingdom, which tended to that purpoſe; ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re Intituled, <hi>The juſt Pretenſions of the King on the Empire;</hi> others, <hi>The Decay of the Empire;</hi> Theſe were the fore-runners of what the King deſign'd to do, that when it ſhould come to paſs, <hi>Europe</hi> ſhould not be ſurpiz'd at it, and the Blow not ſo much ſelt by the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi> It is a Maxim that has
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:44821:42"/>been practis'd in <hi>France</hi> during this Reign, when the Council had a deſign of Oppreſſing the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects by any Impoſition, or to tread them down by any Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, the noiſe of it was ſpread abroad Six Months before, that when the Blow ſhould fall, the People might be prepar'd for it, and ſo found not the Evil ſo great as it really was, becauſe it was expected.</p>
            <p>All the <hi>French</hi> Kings Pretenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons derive from <hi>Charlemain,</hi> who, though King of <hi>France,</hi> was E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected Emperor, but <hi>Charles</hi> being Dead, the Electors were in right of Electing another capable to Govern the Empire, and to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend Chriſtendom, without being oblig'd or wedded to the Perſon of the <hi>French</hi> King.</p>
            <p>But I find, without Diſpute, that the Emperors have much more Right to the Kingdom of <hi>France,</hi> and that it is better
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:44821:42"/>grounded than that of the <hi>French</hi> Kings on the Empire, of which the Three Biſhopricks of <hi>Thoul, Metz,</hi> and <hi>Verdun,</hi> are dependences which <hi>France</hi> has Uſurp'd, and to obtain peace and quiet the Emperor has been forc'd to bid them an eternal Farewel.</p>
            <p>All Hiſtories ſhew us, that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly the <hi>Gauls</hi> did depend of the Empire, and was look'd upon by the Emperors of the Weſt, as an Imperial Dependency, and feuda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory to it; in effect, the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops of <hi>Treves</hi> did take upon them the Quality of Imperial Chancellors in that part; and <hi>Charles</hi> the VIII. King of all <hi>France,</hi> as he was, was not aſham'd to take upon him the Quality of Vicar General and Perpetual of the holy Empire.</p>
            <p>Moreover, <hi>Conrad</hi> being come to <hi>Paris,</hi> caus'd himſelf to be receiv'd there as Superior, by King <hi>Charles,</hi> Sir-named the Simple, and the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:44821:43"/>Emperor <hi>Sigiſmond,</hi> in the Reign of <hi>Lewis</hi> the XI. made his Entry in that Capital City, with all the Marks of Soveraignty, preceded at Noon Day (in imitation of the ancient <hi>Roman</hi> Emporors) by a great number of Torches of White Wax Lighted, took his Seat in the Preſence of the King, in the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, Created Knights, and there it was that he Erected the County of <hi>Savoy</hi> into a Dutchy, and acknowledg'd that Duke as Prince of the Empire. The Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors, no more than the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> over loſe their Righ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and I think they ſhould have th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſome Prerogatives as ſuch Kings, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> own themſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> never loſe any thing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ate, engage, nor ſell.</p>
            <p>But we are not here to rake <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Aſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of the Empire's anci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>gh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, but only to prevent the <hi>French</hi> King<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from making <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>y ones, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>wards to poſſeſs
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:44821:43"/>them, ſeeing that his Generals do publickly declare. That they know no other Right but Power, and the only pleaſure and good-liking of their Monarch, of whom they make a God on Earth, <hi>Viro im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortali.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At this preſent, the <hi>French</hi> King beholds all <hi>Europe</hi> in Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> againſt him, and he finds h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>or well parry that Blow; that <hi>England</hi>'s lifted up Arm threaten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him with a toral Ruine, and becauſe he cannot eaſily withſtand all thoſe Powers that are United againſt him, he endeavours, at leaſt, if he cannot win them to his Party, to divide them from the other, by that Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trality which he propoſes to them, in deſign of accompliſhing two things, if he obtains it.</p>
            <p>The Firſt is, to diminiſh the number of his Enemies, and the ſecond, that by that means he may gain a free acceſs near <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thoſe ſeparated Powers, ſlatter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:44821:44"/>himſelf with the hopes to draw them afterwards to his Party, through advantageous Offers, but much ſooner, if he can but never ſo little rouſe himſelf up again, from that Apoplexy in which he is fallen.</p>
            <p>But the Emperor and his Allies, to break his Meaſures and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy his Deſigns, ought not to allow of any Neutrality to any Prince, State, nor City of the Empire, but to hinder him, if poſſible, from ſoliciting the <hi>Swit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>-Cantons;</hi> on the contrary to g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r them to join to the Empire, and if they cannot be prevail'd with ſo to do, oblige them to call borne thoſe Forces which they have in the <hi>French</hi> Service, or at leaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> permit the raiſing in their Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories a like number of Men by the Emperor and his Allies; it being pre-ſuppos'd, that a State can never be counted Neuter, ſo long as it furniſhes Forces to one of
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:44821:44"/>the Parties that are in Wars to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether; beſides, ſuch a Neutra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity is of evil conſequence to the others that pretend to the ſame: There are but very few States that are not glad to ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours weaken'd, that they may draw advantage from their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders, and get to themſelves the Trade, and to ſee them from a ſecure place ruine one another, while their Neuter Subjects en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich themſelves, and improve by the ſpoil, as the Archbiſhop of <hi>Ment<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> did think to do, if he had not been cheated by <hi>France;</hi> to his great ſorrow he has made tryal of <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV <hi>th's</hi> Maxims, who has no ſooner laid his ſinger on a place, but that he endeavours to thruſt in his whole body, and to drive from thence the Lawful Lord. Though all has known this, yet divers hitherto have been ſurpris'd with it, they call out for help, when they thiink them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:44821:45"/>loſt, as we have ſeen in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers little States which he has ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propriated to himſelf; and he had done the like to <hi>Geneva,</hi> had not the Laudable <hi>Cantons</hi> oppos'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to it. The <hi>Switz</hi> percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty did by that deſign to ſmooth a Path for himſelf into their Country, and into the States of the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> if they durſt but have ſtirr'd never ſo little af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that Conqueſt.</p>
            <p>I now paſs to the Cantons of the <hi>Son<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zers,</hi> by reaſon of their Proximity to the Empire, and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance with the Emperor; they have no cauſe of being better ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied than many others are of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great, if they would but return from that blindneſs where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they are, and make ſome Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections on what has paſs'd, only ſince his Reign; h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>w that he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muſes them on the one ſide, while he is undermining of their Union
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:44821:45"/>on the other, together with their Liberty, and their Power; incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing them ſo cloſe on all ſides, as if he would ſo girt them in, that they ſhould not be able to ſtir themſelves. His Deſign is to make them Tributary, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, but of divers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of Men, when he has <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or them, and when they ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uld be of moſt uſe to him: to that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ends the Uſurpation of the <hi>French County,</hi> which was formerly their Barr, the Fortreſſes of <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> and of <hi>Crenſack,</hi> and ſo many other Forrs and Bridges which the King has cau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>'d of late to be buil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> round their Coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rey.</p>
            <p>It is that way do the <hi>Lewis d'Or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> tend, which the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor does ſo freely ſcatter about in the <hi>Cantons,</hi> and ſo many fair pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and <hi>French</hi> Compliments, with which the Lords are ſed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> rock them aſleep; but in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he mea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> time, I humbly deſire that thoſe
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:44821:46"/>Gentlemen would make a ſerious Reflection on the ill Treatment and Contempt lately put on their Ambaſſadors, and by that they ſhall judge, whether they have any great cauſe to reckon on, and to truſt to the Friendſhip and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of that King; and let them not flatter themſelves, if the King could have made them ſubmit to the <hi>French</hi> Yoak, long ſince had he done that buſineſs, becauſe he well knows the need he has of them, that the <hi>Cantons</hi> can ſupply him with a great number of good Souldiers, and that he can build and reckon on their Alliance. I know that in <hi>Switzerland,</hi> as well as elſewhere, there are Mercenary Spirits, that would willingly Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice their Country to their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Intereſts; who promiſe much to <hi>France,</hi> without conſidering well what they do; and if the King had enter'd into <hi>Germany</hi> as he had purpos'd to do, as I have before
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:44821:46"/>mention'd, the <hi>Cantons</hi> had had great cauſe to fear, that divers Towns whoſe Magiſtrates had been brib'd, had follow'd the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Example of <hi>Strasbourg.</hi> To this purpoſe the King has always endeavour'd to divide them in their hearts, as well as in their Religion.</p>
            <p>But ſome will ſay, that Things have not happen'd ſo, and that they are ſtill in a good Condition. I grant that, and I anſwer that the paſs'd danger ought to render us wiſe for the future; the Swallows know their times, why ſhould Men neglect theirs? Wherefore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all, the <hi>Switzers</hi> ought not to let ſlip ſo fair an Occaſion, by which they may ſet themſelves at reſt for ever. I Conjure them to it, by that which they hold moſt dear in the World, their Liberty, Religion, their Children, and their own Preſervation; let them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member they are born free,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:44821:47"/>that they depend but on God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, and on their Valour, and that they ought to maintain them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in thoſe fair Priviledges, which their Anceſtors have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quir'd to them by their Swords, and their blood; being arriv'd at the moment in which they may preſerve them; they ought not to fall aſleep at the ſound of the <hi>French</hi> Gold, it is not with this as with the Tide, which returns every day; and it may be that <hi>England</hi> ſhall never again be Govern'd by a King repleniſh'd with ſuch good Sentiments, and that ſhall be ſo well fix'd to the General Intereſts of all Chriſtendom, as is that Prince who Reigns there at this preſent. It is a good fortune, which muſt be taken hold of by the foretop, for fear ſhe flyes away. It is not to be doubted, but that at this very preſent, the <hi>French</hi> Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor does indefatigably Labour with the <hi>Cantons,</hi> and that he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:44821:47"/>much more than his Maſter deſigns to perform: and he tails not to tender alſo the Arrears due to them, provided the <hi>Cantons</hi> will permit the raiſing of new Forces, or only accept of a Neutrality. As if the King did offer them any thing more than their own, which he ought to have pay'd them long ſince. I very well know that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Perſons, whoſe eyes this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imburſement cauſes to be open, would willingly grant what the King requires of them, in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief that they might obſerve a Neutrality with that; juſt as if the Emperor had granted it, and at the ſame time permit Forces ſhould be given to his Enemy; which would be two things very incompatible, and which no Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch would ever endure, if he were in any Condition to prevent it. Wherefore I once more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat, that the <hi>Cantons</hi> ought to make ſerious Reflections on the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:44821:48"/>preſent State of <hi>France</hi> in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, and on that of <hi>Europe</hi> in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral; and rouſe up from that dullneſs and Mercenary humour in which they are kept, in the fear the <hi>French</hi> King has, that the <hi>Switzers</hi> ſhould awaken on the ſudden, and open their eyes to their true Intereſt. It lyes at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent but on a ſtrong and generous Reſolution, to get out of all dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, prevent ever relapſing into them again, and ſet themſelves in a Condition to depend on none but themſelves. To this purpoſe, they ought to joyn themſelves to the Empire; and then require from the King that he ſhould demoliſh thoſe Fortreſſes which he has caus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d to be built, contrary to former Treaties, and in caſe of a refuſal by an authentick and general De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, recall their Forces, and with thoſe very Troops that are ſo well Diſciplin'd, and thoſe they have already, go themſelves and execute
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:44821:48"/>that which <hi>France</hi> refuſes them, and pull down thoſe ſtone Tables which he has ſet up. Beſides, let the Lords of that Republick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that the more Souldiers they lend to <hi>France,</hi> the more Men they loſe; whoſe hearts are inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly alienated from their own Country, by Death, by Offices, by Penſions, by Mariages, and ſome by the Change of Religion; and theſe laſt are young Vipers, which will one day gnaw their own Mothers bowels.</p>
            <p>I know that the <hi>Switzers</hi> with divers others, have ſome years ſince fear'd the Forces which <hi>France</hi> has (to make it ſelf dreaded) all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways kept in readineſs, after Peace and after the Truce alſo; which Forces made it to ſpeak with Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, and required nothing but with threatnings; being the only Prince in <hi>Europe</hi> that did ſee him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in a Condition to Undertake, and to Act, before others were in
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:44821:49"/>a Condition to Defend themſelves, which made him to be fear'd by his Neighbours, and procur'd him Alliances, but particularly that of King <hi>James,</hi> with which he thought himſelf ſufficiently ſtrong to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all <hi>Europe,</hi> beginning as I have already ſaid, by the United Provinces.</p>
            <p>I doubt not but all theſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations might have a great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence over the <hi>Cantons,</hi> and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige the <hi>Switzers</hi> to grant to <hi>France</hi> that which perhaps they had not done at any other time, but now the ſtorm is blown over, the Cauſe of that Pride with which the King did threaten, being vaniſh'd into ſmoak, the fear ought to ceaſe alſo, and there ought not to remain any conſideration ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to retain the <hi>Switzers</hi> under the Rod of <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIVth. Let them return to their priſtine Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and to their right Intereſt. Let thoſe Gentlemen know, that
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:44821:49"/>Kings are Great no longer than they are happy, and that they are fear'd no longer than their good fortune laſts. I therefore maintain, that that Imperiouſneſs (with which <hi>France</hi> was us'd to draw advantages from the <hi>Cantons</hi>) is at an end, now that it finds it ſelf over-whelm'd from all ſides, that all its Alliances on which it found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed all its new Uſurpations, are vaniſh'd, and that at this preſent he has almoſt as many Enemies, as there are Princes in <hi>Europe.</hi> If they have not yet all declar'd, they will not ſtay long, they only wait to ſee the Dance begin, to joyn themſelves with the Allies, as we have lately ſeen the Republick of <hi>Liege,</hi> which has ſcorn'd its threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings, and embrac'd that Party which it apprehended to be the moſt advantageous, and the moſt neceſſary for its State. Which ſufficiently ſhews the ſmall regard that it had at preſent for the <hi>French</hi>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:44821:50"/>King, who is no longer in a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of doing any great Damage in an open War, ſince <hi>England</hi> h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s turn'd the Muzzle of her Cannons againſt him, and that the Prince on whoſe Alliance he ſo ſtrongly built his hopes, is no longer in a Condition to do any good or hurt to <hi>Europe;</hi> for in lieu of ſuccou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his Allie, he himſelf ſtands in need of him: he drains <hi>France;</hi> the Calf in time will kill the Cow, with drawing her too hard; it is a new Charge to <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV, and that Unfortunate Prince ſees himſelf on the brink of a Precipice, which by a ſpecial Grace from Heaven he may yet avoid, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiring into ſome Convent.</p>
            <p>The Laudable <hi>Cantons</hi> ought to make other Reflections, and have other Conſiderations at preſent than they formerly had; they ſhould too lift up their Eyes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>England,</hi> and behold Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:44821:50"/>
               <hi>Britanick</hi> Majeſty <hi>William</hi> the IIId as their Friend and Allie, profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the ſame Religion, and who, during His Reign, will make it a point of Generoſity, and of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to Succour them againſt all the Aſſaults of the <hi>French</hi> King. If they declare themſelves, both through <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Tye of Communion, and that of Eſteem, which that Great Prince has for them, even His great and generous Deſigns ought to ſerve to make them re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urn to their ancient Rights and Liberties, cauſe their aincent Limits <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be made good again for greater <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecurity; but then they ought not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o remain quiet all the while, with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir arms folded, but labour with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll their power, and aſſiſt to bring <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bout ſo great a good, and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ange, which the Heavens offers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem. To that purpoſe, they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould Exemplarily puniſh all thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ercinary Perſons, whoſe hands, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d their Honours have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:44821:51"/>with the <hi>French</hi> Money. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſantly cauſe their Forces to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, which are in the <hi>French</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; in caſe of diſobedience, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare them Rebels, and Confiſcate their Means; oblige thoſe Fathers who have Children there, to call them home on great Mulcts, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to admit to any Employ nor Dignity either in Church or State, all ſuch as ſhall contradict theſe Orders, and never ceaſe 'till the Fortreſſes are demoliſh'd, and <hi>Burgundy,</hi> the <hi>French County, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſace,</hi> and <hi>Lorain</hi> reſtor'd to their ancient Maſters and Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns, that they may be as ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Bulwarks to the <hi>Cantons:</hi> all which they can eaſily do in this Conjuncture, which at this preſent ſo favourably offers it ſelf, and which they ought not to let ſlip, ſeeing there is at this preſent, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Proteſtant and the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick <hi>Cantons</hi> ſo good a Harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and firm Union, that the Pope
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:44821:51"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s wholly inclin'd to cauſe thoſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is Party to keep it ſtrictly as a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ceſſary good for the quiet of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tendom,</hi> and the ſafety of <hi>Europe,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s well as to abate the Pride of <hi>France:</hi> All this will happen, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eclaring for the Emperor and Empire.</p>
            <p>I come now to <hi>Spain,</hi> formerly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir Soveraigns Govern'd from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ithin their Cloſets, a good part <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the World, but ſince <hi>Philip</hi> the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> its great Power has began to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecay; and that of the Kings of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rance</hi> to increaſe, at the ſame time <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat that of the Catholick Kings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecreaſed. I ſhall not ſeek after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Cauſes of it, becauſe that is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>de my Subject; I ſhall only ſay <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y the by, that the Liberty of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>onſcience in <hi>France</hi> has much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ntributed to its Elevation; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at contrary-wiſe, the privation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it in <hi>Spain,</hi> has caus'd there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eat Evils, and the loſs of Trade, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich is the Soul of States and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ngdoms.</p>
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:44821:52"/>
            <p>The Marriages which the Kings of <hi>Spain</hi> have Contracted with <hi>France,</hi> have been ſo many Levens of Diſcord, and of War, which have always prov'd very hurtful to <hi>Spain;</hi> and not to go back any further than to the late Queen, who was a <hi>French</hi> Woman as much by inclination, as ſhe was by Birth who by the ſubtle and dextrous Counſel of the King her Uncle'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Ambaſſadors, had always ſome new buſineſs to propoſe to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> King her Husband, who moſt ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly lov'd her. By thoſe mean<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that Princeſs had acquir'd a grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> aſcendent over the King's min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſometimes prejudicial to the go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of his Kingdom; for whoſe proſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſhe had not all the Conſider<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion ſhe ought to have had; ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> having no Children to Succeed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it, and ſtill in fears, that remaini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Barren, after ſome conſidera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> time ſhe might be Divorc'd, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Laws and Statut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of that Kingdom<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <pb n="101" facs="tcp:44821:52"/>
            <p>All the ſtudy of the ſaid Queen was (but moſt particularly a little before her death) to labour hard for the advantage of <hi>France;</hi> and at the laſt, her greateſt buſineſs was, to intercede with the King for that Money which was come to <hi>Cadiz,</hi> on the <hi>French</hi> Account, in the laſt Fleet that was come from the <hi>Indies.</hi> And we have ſeen that contrary to the right Policy, and the true Intereſt of <hi>Spain,</hi> the Queen ſucceded in it, for that Money ought to have been ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtred under the King's Seal, 'till the Council had ſeen what Courſe the Affairs of <hi>Europe</hi> had taken in theſe preſent Conjunctures. <hi>Spain</hi> had no want of pretences, it had juſt cauſe to have kept back, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out blame, thoſe 14 Millions, which of truth were Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands, ſeeing that no ſtrangers have the liberty to negotiate in the <hi>Spaniſh Indies,</hi> under pain of Confiſcation, 'till his Catholick
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:44821:53"/>Majeſty had ſeen what ſatisfaction he ſhould receive from <hi>France,</hi> on all his other Demands and Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; and in caſe he receiv'd none, he then might have been his own Pay-Maſter, as it is frequently practis'd, even amongſt private Perſons; but what I ſay here, is, <hi>after Death the Phyſician,</hi> ſeeing the Birds are flown, there is no remedy for this time, but for the future, the Perſons concern'd, will conſider better.</p>
            <p>Another of the late Queens ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, was to bring the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick King to accept of a Neutrality which <hi>France</hi> offer'd him; that joyn'd to the recovering of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney we laſtly mention'd, was the only buſineſs of the Ambaſſador <hi>Rebenac:</hi> But while they were thus acting againſt the Intereſts of <hi>Spain,</hi> God has taken that Queen away in the prime of her Age, before ſhe could render that laſt piece of ſervice to her Uncle the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:44821:53"/>
               <hi>French</hi> King, which was ſo neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to him at this preſent. How can it be help'd? I confeſs that it is a very great loſs for <hi>France,</hi> but it muſt comfort it ſelf, as <hi>Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in</hi> has done, for parting with the 14 Millions. <hi>France,</hi> ever ſlye and cunning, made uſe of a ſpecious pretence to oblige the King of <hi>Spain</hi> to accept of the Neutrality, endeavouring to perſwad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him, that by that means he ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Mediator betwixt <hi>France</hi> and the Empire, as if the Moſt Chriſtian King did not know the ſtrict Union there is betwixt thoſe two Monarchs, which make but one Houſe, and Family. Thus their intereſt being but one, and that of the Emperor being the ſame with that of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> which is well known to his Chriſtian Majeſty; let any judge, whether <hi>France</hi> being cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of that Truth (which is not to be doubted) had a deſire to
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:44821:54"/>referr her Concerns into the hands of the Catholick King, except ſhe were at the very laſt gaſp, not knowing what Saint to Pray to. But the moſt probable, and the moſt receiv'd Opinion is, that the <hi>French</hi> King makes his laſt Efforts to diminiſh the number of its Enemies: and though <hi>Spain</hi> ſhould be ſo weak, as the <hi>French Partiſans</hi> would make us believe it is, and that at moſt it could but ſtand on the Defenſive part: The <hi>French</hi> muſt have two Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies on foot, to prevent the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards</hi> from advancing. The one in <hi>Catalonia,</hi> and the other in <hi>Flanders,</hi> and peradventure a third in <hi>Navarre,</hi> which might take him up at leaſt Fifty Thouſand Men, which he might have employ'd elſewhere. If <hi>Spain</hi> had accepted of that Neutrality, and if <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great, mean time had overcame the Empire, what would have become of <hi>Spain</hi>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:44821:54"/>afterwards? after all what aſſurance has it that <hi>France</hi> would more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly obſerve the Neutrality than it has the Peace, and the Truce, and who had been its Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that when the <hi>French</hi> King had had an opportunity, he had not fallen on ſome place of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> and it may be, on <hi>Navarre,</hi> and <hi>Mentz</hi> all at one time, when the Governours were fallen aſleep in the arms of a Neutrality, as in a deep Lethargy, as they did preſently after the Peace of <hi>Nimeguen;</hi> in which the Marqueſs of <hi>Grana</hi> was repoſing at eaſe, fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling his Purſe, by ſparing the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining of a number of Forces, which were ſo neceſſary to him, while he had to do with ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous a Neighbour, who no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger remember'd Treaties, than while he Sign'd them, becauſe they were at that time of uſe to him, he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver wanting afterwards Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, when he would break them.</p>
            <pb n="106" facs="tcp:44821:55"/>
            <p>A Neutrality in this juncture of time, is very hurtful to <hi>Spain,</hi> and to its Allies; but above all to the Emperor and to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, <hi>Spain</hi> would do, as if when Two Brothers were Attack'd, one ſhould look on his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion with foulded Armes, while he was diveſted of all, expecting his turn to be next; whereas, if they both defended themſelves at once, they might either overcome their Enemy, or drive him away. What aſſurances has <hi>Spain,</hi> that if the <hi>French</hi> King could overcome the Empire, he would not Attack it next, as he would doubtleſs do? Wherefore, his Catholick Majeſty ought to make a laſt Effort; in this preſent Conjuncture, he ought to conſider th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t <hi>France</hi> has taken from him <hi>Liſle, Valiencienne, Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bray, St. Omer, Erre,</hi> and many other places in the Provinces of <hi>Flanders, Namur, Hainau, Luxem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg,</hi> and in fine, the City of
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:44821:55"/>
               <hi>Luxembourg,</hi> which was as a Bull work to the reſt of <hi>Flanders</hi> and of <hi>Brabant,</hi> as well as to the other Provinces, while <hi>England</hi> remain'd with folded Arms againſt its own proper Intereſt, having been brib'd to let <hi>France</hi> do what it pleas'd. King <hi>James,</hi> as zealous a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick as he was, did conſent that <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. ſhould ſeize on the remainder of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> while he ſhould ſit himſelf with the <hi>Spaniſh Indies,</hi> as his Ally had promiſed him he ſhould; thus did they, without any ſcruple, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt their Catholick Neighbours of their Rights, and ſhar'd them amongſt them, without caſting of Lots. If that Prince had not abandon'd the Throne, that Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trality might have been very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable; but now the Caſe is alter'd, in quitting of the Crown, he has Diſarm'd himſelf, he is now but like a Waſp without a Sting, which buzzes about, but cannot
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:44821:56"/>ſting. <hi>Spain</hi> has loſt in him a conceal'd Enemy, and a falſe Ally, who ſold to <hi>France</hi> that which belong'd not to him, and that conſented to the ſeizing on Goods wherein he had no ſhare; but God, who laughs at the deſign of Men, would not permit that thoſe of <hi>James</hi> the II. ſhould come to perfection. Providence, for the ſafety of <hi>Europe,</hi> has beſtow'd his place to another Prince, and has conducted, as 'twere by the hand, <hi>William</hi> the III. to the Throne; he, according to all appearance, is to be the Inſtrument through which God will give reſt to Chriſtendom. Thus <hi>Spain,</hi> in lieu of an Enemy which it had in <hi>James</hi> the II. late King of <hi>England,</hi> recovers in his Succeſſor a good Friend and Ally, faithful to his Word, and who being join'd to his Allies, may all together labour effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to eſtabliſh the King of <hi>Spain</hi> in his ancient Rights and Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:44821:56"/>and cauſe <hi>France</hi> to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore what it had Uſurped from it.</p>
            <p>This Foundation being as firm as it is certain, <hi>Spain</hi> ought to join with thoſe who labour for its reſt and quiet, by that of all <hi>Europe,</hi> to put in a readineſs all its Forces, in <hi>Catalonia, Navarre,</hi> and above all in the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> where the People muſt copiouſly bleed their Purſes, towards the Entertainment of an Army, capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to defend it ſelf againſt the <hi>French</hi> Aſſaults; let them conſider the barbarouſneſs and inhumanity with which they have Treated thoſe Towns that have ſubmitted to them, under good Capitula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and ſuch Conditions as had been made by the Dauphin himſelf; let them make Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on the cruelty with which the <hi>French</hi> King has treated his own Subjects, againſt the promis'd Faith, and if after that, the humour takes them to ſubmit to the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:44821:57"/>
               <hi>French</hi> Yoke, it may then be ſaid of them, as it is ſaid of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain People, that they are born to ſlavery.</p>
            <p>Let <hi>Spain</hi> further conſider, the great pretenſions the Dauphin thinks to have on the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> on a material Right, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the Oaths and Renunciati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which the King his Father made of them at the <hi>Pirenean</hi> Peace and at the time of his Marriage with the <hi>Infanta,</hi> on the Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the <hi>Pheſants,</hi> at the foot of the Altar, communicating at the greateſt and ſublimeſt Miſtery that is in the Catholick Church, which he has afterwards ſlighted; and if he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers taking Poſſeſſion of what he pretends to, it is not that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounces it, time deprives him of none of his Rights, it is only for want of an opportunity which has not yet been favourable e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to him, and that his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, the States of the United
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:44821:57"/>Provinces, are a ſtumbling block to him, and a perpetual Obſtacle, which he could never ſo well mannage as he did <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es</hi> the II. becauſe thoſe Lords know better their Intereſt, than that poor Prince ever did. We know that <hi>Flanders</hi> has always been a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one to pick for the <hi>Fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> King<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and ſo long as they will find ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to gnaw on they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ll not think of going to <hi>Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in;</hi> but if they had once made an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd of that bit, and well digeſted it, if that which employs them on that ſide was over, what would hinder them from pouring all their Forces into <hi>Catalenia</hi> and <hi>Navarr<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and from entring with a powerful Army in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Spain,</hi> and even March to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drid?</hi> wherefore, the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt is to ſtrongly unite it ſelf at this preſent with the Empire, with <hi>England,</hi> and with the United Provinces, to ſolicite them, not to lay down their Arms, till they
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:44821:58"/>have recover'd <hi>Burgundy,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> County, all the Uſurped Cities in <hi>Flanders, Hainan, Namur,</hi> and <hi>Luxembourg;</hi> without which, it will in ſucceſs of time, relapſe again into the ſame Straits as it hath been in the Reigns of <hi>Charles</hi> the II. and <hi>James</hi> the II. of <hi>Great Britain;</hi> if once for all, it delivers not it ſelf at this preſent from that danger, whence it ſeems already to revive and recover, by the ſudden change of Affairs in <hi>England.</hi> Mean time, let the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Council be wary not to be deceiv'd by the <hi>French</hi> Illuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, who promiſes all when trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and ſtands in need of help, who ruines it ſelf with Promiſes, but reſtores it ſelf again with performing none of them, more abounding in Crafts than in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity; the danger paſs'd, a Fig for the Saint; let the ſame Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil hold for certain, that when ever the <hi>French</hi> King has any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:44821:58"/>for <hi>Spain,</hi> it is a ſign he is at the laſt gaſp, and that he knows not whither elſe to go: If that Council can be fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of this Truth, it will not fail to adviſe his Catholick Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, to make all his Efforts, and to ſend all the Money he can poſſible to the Governour of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> to put themſelves in a condition to ſuſtain the firſt fury of the <hi>French,</hi> after which there is nothing more to fear, for the Allies will give it ſo much Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, even in <hi>France</hi> it ſelf, that its King will no longer think of going to attack others, for ſo ſoon as the <hi>Germans</hi> and the <hi>Hollanders</hi> ſhall have clear'd the Countries of <hi>Colen, Juliers,</hi> and <hi>Treves,</hi> the Governour of the <hi>Netherlands</hi> ſhall not want Men, as he has al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready experienc'd by that Succour which has been ſent him: But the Marquiſs of <hi>Guaſtanaga</hi> ought not to grow ſupine upon this,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:44821:59"/>he ought to put himſelf in a condition to help himſelf, he may by that acquire a great deal of Glory, in the condition thoſe Provinces which depend of his Government are in; above all, he ought very well to ſupply the Town of <hi>Namur,</hi> its Neighbour has Courted it long, becauſe it opens to him a fair and large way all along the River <hi>Meuſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I add to what I have ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, concerning the Death of the Queen of <hi>Spain,</hi> that ſeeing ſhe has left no Succeſſor, through her Barrenneſs, to the Crown of <hi>Spain,</hi> ſo neceſſary for the good of the Kingdom, and for the quiet of Chriſtendom, it appear'd as a kind of neceſſity for the one and the other, that the King ſhould forthwith think of entring into a ſecond Marriage with ſome Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of a fruitful Family; I know that policy (to endeavour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover <hi>Portugal</hi>) would adviſe to
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:44821:59"/>look on that <hi>Infanta,</hi> but the ſterility of the Queen of <hi>England</hi> her Aunt, has made the Council of <hi>Spain</hi> to fear falling into the ſame accident again; if <hi>France</hi> had had more Princeſſes to Marry that had been worthy of his Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Majeſty's Choice, (as <hi>Spain</hi> may thank God it had not) it had not fail'd to propoſe them, to make up a match, in the hopes thereby to have obtain'd a Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trality, becauſe all thoſe Marriages have always produc'd ſome ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages to <hi>France.</hi> But having nothing to fear that way, <hi>Spain</hi> has been oblig'd to turn towards <hi>Germany,</hi> and to fix in the Family of the Prince <hi>Palatin Nienbourg,</hi> there was ſtill remaining there a beautiful Princeſs, Siſter to the Empreſs, and to the Queen of <hi>Portugal;</hi> though elder than this laſt, ſhe had no mind to go to <hi>Portugal,</hi> by ſome certain fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge ſhe had, ſuch a Marriage
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:44821:60"/>would have contracted a more ſtrict Allianee betwixt thoſe Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and <hi>Portugal;</hi> the <hi>German</hi> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are uſually fruitful, that Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs comes not from a Houſe, whoſe Intereſt ſhould make them to deſire Barrenneſs, there being therefore nothing to ſear on that ſide, there is no queſtion but that the Queen-Mother has us'd all her Power, as well as the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, to accompliſh it; and that on the contrary, the <hi>French</hi> Emiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries have labour'd with all their ſubtleties to prevent it; but their ill fortune has been ſuch, that their Credit has been very incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable in thoſe Courts; they are like thoſe petty Saints, who no longer work Miracles, and whoſe Feaſts are over; their falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood is but too well known al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready all over <hi>Europe,</hi> wherefore now they begin to take their March into the new World, to the Kingdoms of <hi>China</hi> and of <hi>Siam,</hi>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:44821:60"/>where thoſe good People believe that all Perſons are as honeſt as themſelves, ſo that it will not be difficult for the <hi>French</hi> to impoſe upon them; but as to <hi>Europe,</hi> we are now in a time that no Prince will have any Alliance will <hi>France,</hi> much leſs with any of its Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes as Wives, ſeeing there is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral complaint of them, for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving caus'd Diſorders in all the States they came to.</p>
            <p>The United Provinces are high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concern'd to keep low the <hi>French</hi> King, to take from him all deſires of moleſting them, nor to go ſo far towards them, as the Conqueſt of the <hi>Netherlands</hi> of <hi>Spain.</hi> It was always the aim of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great, according to the advice of Mounſieur <hi>de Sulli,</hi> formerly Ambaſſador of <hi>France</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> in the time of <hi>Henry</hi> the IV. who gave him to obſerve, that the conjunction of the United Provinces with <hi>France,</hi> was the
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:44821:61"/>only means to reſtore it to its an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Grandeur, and to render it Superior to all the reſt of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Formerly the <hi>French</hi> Kings had their folly fix'd on <hi>Italy,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, in imitation of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Romans,</hi> that it was the Gate they were to paſs through to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to the Univerſal Monarchy, but having found that way too <hi>Thorny,</hi> and that Country having frequently been the Church-yard of the <hi>French,</hi> they have grown weary of it, and have turn'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves towards the Low-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, where hitherto <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. has ſucceeded better, and he had found out a means to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue there his Progreſs, if the Heavens had not prevented it, by the change in <hi>England.</hi> I know that the United Provinces had had nothing to fear, if the <hi>Netherlands</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> had been in a condition to maintain themſelves with their own ſtrength, or if the late Kings
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:44821:61"/>of <hi>England</hi> had had the ſame Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents which Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> had, and if <hi>Charles</hi> and <hi>James</hi> the Seconds had ſaid to Monſieur <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillon,</hi> that which that Queen ſaid to Monſieur of <hi>Sulli, That neither</hi> France <hi>nor</hi> England, <hi>nor any other Prince, had any thing to pretend to the</hi> Netherlands, <hi>that ſhe ſhould not ſuffer that the King his Maſter ſhould have any thoughts that way.</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the <hi>Lewis D'Ors</hi> were not currant in thoſe Days in that Great Princeſſes Court, as they have ſince been, and that that Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs did better underſtand her own true Intereſt, than divers Kings who have ſucceeded her have done. But thanks to Heaven, thoſe Kings are paſs'd, and God has at this preſent ſeated on the Throne a King who underſtands very well his Intereſt, and that of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, much better than did his Predeceſſor, and who following the Traces of that Great Princeſs)
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:44821:62"/>was no ſooner got to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, but he ſent back Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Barillon,</hi> to tell his Maſter, that he had nothing to do in the <hi>Netherland,</hi> end that he would prevent him from any fur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r Uſurpation in thoſe parts The Elevation of that Great P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>e o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Throne of <hi>England,</hi> is a fatal Blow to the greatneſs of <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. (we muſt have ſo much Charity as to confeſs it) but at the ſame time it produces the Quier and Repoſe of all <hi>Europe;</hi> it is a Bit clapp'd in the <hi>French</hi> Kings Mouth, which retains him from a running ſo far as to the United Provinces, and that ſhelters them from all his Inſultations, and from all his Threatnings, and furniſhes them at the ſame time with M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ans to reſiſt him vigorouſly, and to clip his Wings ſo ſhort, that he may not fly any more beyond his juſt bounds; it is a bitter Pill which he is forc'd to ſwallow, and which
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:44821:62"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill make him to diſgorge, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> re-eſtabliſh thoſe bounds which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> had remov'd during his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours weakneſſes, in a profound <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd univerſal Peace.</p>
            <p>The United Provinces, as well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> divers other States, find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lves deliver'd now from that dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er that threatned them, and it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> now their turn to ſpeak aloud, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nding themſelves aſſiſted by ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>owerful an Allie as <hi>England;</hi> they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ay demand the Reſtitution of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Places of the <hi>Spaniſh Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nds,</hi> which have been taken from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>em ſince the Peace of the <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eans,</hi> becauſe thoſe places ſerve <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> preſerve them, and as bars that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a large <hi>Territory</hi> betwixt them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ſo dangerous a Prince; beſides <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat, the damage they have ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ain'd in their Trade is very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable and gives them cauſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reat pretenſions. <hi>France</hi> has ſup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanted and deceiv'd them in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers occaſions, and it has endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:44821:63"/>to lull them aſleep, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the laſt place, by the <hi>Count</hi> d'<hi>Avaux</hi> its Ambaſſador; through vain promiſes (which Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Limojou</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King's Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moner, call'd <hi>Illuſory</hi>) and in which there was no ſincerity nor good Faith, as we have ſeen in all his Proceedings after the Peace of <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> and that it has been but a continual Uſurpation. That this King might the longer and with more ſafety enjoy thoſe Places that he had Uſurped, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Truce was patch'd up for Twenty Years, during a full Peace, which he likewiſe broke in few Years after. After he had Fortified thoſe Conquer'd Places, made his Alliance with <hi>James</hi> the II. and deſtroy'd (by an unheard of Cruelty which is natural to him) the Proteſtants in his own Kingdom, as he aſſure<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by his Declaration of the revoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Edict of <hi>Nants,</hi> that he had made that Truce but in
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:44821:63"/>order to deſtroy them, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the Proteſtations to the contrary, which the Count <hi>d'Avaux</hi> had made to obtain it; and to deceive with more eaſe, in the opinion, that after he had made an end with thoſe Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, whom he accus'd of having <hi>Dutch</hi> Hearts, and Intelligences with them, 'twas to that end that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſeiſure tended, which was made of all the Books and Papers belonging to their Conſiſtories, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hroughout the whole Kingdom, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o know the Sums they had ſent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nto <hi>Holland</hi> during the War; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ſeconded by the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and</hi> (then Reigning) he ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ver-run the United Provinces, and leave for a time thoſe of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iards</hi>) conſidering them always he only ones that could croſs his Deſigns, and hinder him from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aking his great Conqueſts over <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urope.</hi> But now Fortune has <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urn'd her back to him, and by
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:44821:64"/>the event, we find that he has not caſt up right, and that his <hi>Moſt Chriſtian Majeſty</hi> had not reckon'd on the Elevation of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> to the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> by that fall of his Ally; who has broken all his Meaſures, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy'd his Alliances, open'd a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> way to the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ares to attack him in his own Hold, and to reduce him to Guard his own Kingdom no longer to think, but to defend himſelf; it is no longer now th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> time of the Peace of <hi>Nimegu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> which was made up on its conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, but through the Treacher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>France,</hi> as the baſeneſs wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which it has obſerv'd it, as we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> as the Treatiſes of Trade, ſhew <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſufficiently; and that the Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> had quite another aim than th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> States-General had propos'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> themſelves at the concluſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that Peace, and afterwards of the Truce. Seeing that the King h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> violated all Trading, and decla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:44821:64"/>War to the United Provinces, on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he frivolous pretence, and on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ccount of a ſorry Prieſt, the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal of <hi>Furſtemburg,</hi> a Rebel to his Lawful Soveraign the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and to his Superior the Pope; who during his whole Life, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ieu of adhering to the Service of the Church, to which he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd himſelf, has made it his buſineſs to diſturb Chriſtendom, and to give occaſion to ſpill blood in <hi>Europe,</hi> and notwithſtanding all that, the <hi>French</hi> King has pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd the Intereſt and Friendſhip of that Man, odious to God and Men, to that of their high and mighty Powers, and to their Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liances, which he had ſought after with ſo much earneſtneſs and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations, by the Peace in 1678. Thus <hi>France</hi> having firſt broke, the States ought to make uſe of the means which God puts in their hands, by the aſſiſtance of the revolution of <hi>England,</hi> which has
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:44821:65"/>not only produc'd them a ſtrict Alliance and ſincere Union but a conſiderable Aſſiſtance alſo that by that Union and that mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Aſſiſtance, they may oblige the <hi>French</hi> King to repent of his unjuſt Proceedings, of all thoſe barbarous Actions and Oppreſſions which he has committed in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,</hi> to bring him back to Reaſon and Juſtice, and to put him in a condition to make no Innovations for the future, ſo long as that happy time ſhall laſt for thoſe Two Nations; they both ought there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to make a laſt Effort to maintain themſelves in that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious liberty, which they at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent enjoy, by a ſpecial favour of Heaven, that is that ineſtimable Gem which <hi>France</hi> has endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to Raviſh from thoſe hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Provinces; but God having deliver'd them from all the Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Great, and from the deſign he had projected
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:44821:65"/>to entirely deſtroy them, he muſt be frighted in his turn, and his Court muſt be fill'd with ſuch a terrour as he never has had ſince his coming to the Crown, which may ſurpaſs that which he had at the Baricado of <hi>Paris,</hi> ſince he has no longer in his Kingdom thoſe that delivered him from it, and who he has ſince ſo ill rewarded.</p>
            <p>There needs but a deſcent on his Coaſts to give it him in good ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, and that is therefore what he apprehends the moſt, and that unhinges him before hand, finding the heart of his Kingdom tainted, and the Enemy at home, who waits but for an opportunity to declare. It is not a <hi>Sampſon</hi> who is no longer tied with ſuch new Cords as never were ſtrong enough to retain him, and to ſtop him; but a <hi>Sampſon</hi> whoſe Locks are cut, and whoſe Eyes are put out, who turns and winds on all ſides, to find out ſome body to lead him
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:44821:66"/>out of the Precipice wherein he finds himſelf; he has given the hand of Aſſociation to the Grand <hi>Seignior,</hi> he will ſoon find a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence for it, it is doubtleſs, he'll ſay in his <hi>Manifeſt,</hi> to endeavour to Convert him to the Catholick Faith, for that is the wet ſheet with which he covers himſelf at preſent againſt the ſtorm which is going to fall on his head, which grows giddy ſo ſoon as he thinks on that deſcent; five hundred leagues of Coaſt confound him, not knowing where his Enemies will Land; there needs but ſome falſe allarm, and at the ſame time a real deſcent, to ſet all thoſe Troops he has along the Coaſts in diſorder. Joyn to that the attack at the ſame time of his Enemies by Land, he muſt undoubtedly bow under thoſe preſſures, and much more yet, if ever the Allies are ſo happy as to enter into the heart of his Kingdom, then he may pack up
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:44821:66"/>his tools, and go ſeek in <hi>Poland</hi> that which King <hi>James</hi> has found with him; for to follow him to <hi>Rome,</hi> he would not be better wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come there than the Marqueſs <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vardin.</hi> 'Tis his own Concern, let him look to it betimes, that King knows that it is impoſſible for him to prevent a deſcent, let him keep never ſo good a Guard by Land, and though he be never ſo ſtrong at Sea, he has too much of ſhore to keep, wherefore he has order'd his Generals to burn his own Country ten Miles round, when ever the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſet footing on it, and to his Fleet to retire into the Mediterranian, where he pretends to be the Lord of the Sea.</p>
            <p>But 'tis likely that his Reign will be but ſhort there, for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> having ſufficiency of Ships, it will be eaſie for them to drive it into the Port of <hi>Tholon,</hi> where yet it will not be abſolutely ſecure, thirty good Veſſels will
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:44821:67"/>make them flye to it, having no longer any place of retreat in <hi>Spain,</hi> and the <hi>Italians</hi> not being able to endure them ſince the buſineſs of <hi>Genoua. England,</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> need not to ſtrain very hard to fit out together 120 Sail of Ships, yet that number will be ſufficient to overcome <hi>France</hi> by Sea, and to ſet that Kingdom into the higheſt Conſternation. In the Year 1673. <hi>De Ruiter</hi> (that great Sea Heroe, whoſe Memory, and Val<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur ſhall laſt as long as the Worl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) with a much leſs number of Forces did beat the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> joyn'd together againſt that State; but now that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fleet ſhall be joyn'd to that of the United Provinces, <hi>France</hi> will be extreamly put to it, and Monſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur of <hi>Segnelai</hi> will have as much need of good Counſel as of Money; but ſay the <hi>French,</hi> if we can do nothing in <hi>Europe,</hi> we will preſerve our ſelves for <hi>America;</hi>
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:44821:67"/>where they think they will do much in ruining ſome Plantations of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Dutch</hi> that have ſettled themſelves there, during the time that the Cities and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces of <hi>France</hi> will be ruining; mean time that fear that he ſhall cauſe to the Savages, will not Cure him of his.</p>
            <p>The good diſpoſition in which all <hi>Europe</hi> is, and the Revolution of <hi>England,</hi> ought highly to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage the States of the United Provinces, now that they find themſelves ſupported by all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Princes, who have with their High and Mightineſſes but one and the ſame Deſign, which is to pull down the Pride of <hi>France,</hi> and that in deſtroying their Common Enemies, they may find themſelves deliver'd from future danger, by the ſole motion of <hi>England.</hi> It is another advantage to the ſaid Provinces, to find themſelves in good Intelligence with their nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:44821:68"/>reſt Neighbours, who are at their door, and that the Arch-Biſhops, and Biſhops of <hi>Colen, Munſter,</hi> and <hi>Liege,</hi> are all Unanimouſly bent to embrace their Intereſt, and that <hi>France</hi> can no longer do in regard to thoſe Prelates, that which ſhe did in the year 1672. But on the contrary, they joyn now with the good party, to oppoſe themſelves, as do their Allies, to the <hi>French</hi> King's Inſultations, who endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to make us believe that he has ſtill very great Ties with <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark,</hi> ſeeing that in his Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the 12th of laſt <hi>March,</hi> he grants to all thoſe Refuged Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that have left his Kingdom, half of thoſe Revenues they left there behind them, yet with that Proviſo, that the Officers ſhall go and ſerve in the Troops of the King of <hi>Denmark.</hi> But becauſe that Kingdom cannot do well with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Trade with <hi>Holland,</hi> it ſeems that it would be a good piece of
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:44821:68"/>Policy to make him expound him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, for it would be a breach which his <hi>Daniſh</hi> Majeſty would make to the Alliances, and he would be falling in his Faith in the Treaties, to con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent that Officers ſhould be drawn out of the Troops of his Allies; beſides it ſeems as if the Affairs of <hi>Europe</hi> could not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit at this time any Neutrality to any Prince under what pretence ſoever: that being granted, <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> ought to make his Choice, and in his Choice, to conſider well the advantage he draws from the United Provinces, the Trade and Profit that reſults from it to his Subjects, and the advantage that the King's Treaſure receives by the Entries and Exportations, (and let them take care not to fall again in the ſame Conſternation, in which they were the laſt year, for ſcarce would the Affairs ſettle again a ſecond time) on the contrary, he can draw no Succour from <hi>France</hi>
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:44821:69"/>in the preſent Condition it is, and though it promiſes to keep it in the poſſeſſion of <hi>Holſtein,</hi> that can be but a Chymerical Promiſe, ſeeing <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIVth can no longer preſerve his own Provinces, nor keep his Cities, part of which he undermines, through a foreſight he has, to be oblig'd to abandon them at the approach of ſo many Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. Thus ought <hi>Denmark</hi> Inviola<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly to joyn it ſelf to that whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h is ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>id, which is Uniting with the United Provinces, have never any thing to unravel which may br ak <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Alliance, nor give occ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on to come to a Rupture, and follow their Intereſt, as the Shadow follows the Body, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerouſly contemn ſome pitiful Penſion, ill pay'd at the beſt, which <hi>France</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffers; it is a broken Reed which will hurt his hand, and a <hi>Will' oth' Wiſp,</hi> which leads to a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipice. L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t his <hi>Daniſh</hi> Majeſty but repreſent to himſelf the advantage
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:44821:69"/>of being free, and that a King ought to depend but of God, and of his own Sword: it is good being in a Condition of making Choice, and of following ones true Intereſt, without being tied by Penſion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, which are but gilded Shackles, that are not the lighter for it, <hi>Sweed,</hi> which the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> has continually at his heels, and who has no Cauſe, no more than many others, of praiſing <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIVth, not to have any Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion for thoſe Powers that ſhall Allie themſelves with that Monarch, who det<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ns from him the Dutchy of <hi>Deux-Pont,</hi> and conſiderable Sums of Arrears due to him, which he would never pay in ſpight, becauſe his <hi>Sweediſh</hi> Majeſty would not continue with him the Alliances which had been Contracted. The ſame will happen to <hi>Denmark,</hi> if they take not care beforehand; But when it once finds it ſelf deceiv'd, then will it have
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:44821:70"/>recourſe to the States of the Unired Provinces; and to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror, but perhaps a little too lat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; mean time, it cannot be thought that the Emperor, and the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Empire will look with a quiet temper on the Alliances of the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> with their commou Enemies, nor even that he ſhould remain Neuter, for ſtill that is the way to ſerve him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>directly, and to give the People the means to carry into <hi>France</hi> all the Proviſion that it will ſtand in want of, their Merchants growing Rich by the Spoll of thoſe that Fight. I would gladly ſee how the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> would defend himſelf, when his Allie <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIVth ſhall ask him for Powder, and Salt-peter for his Money, which is that he has moſt need of at preſent. Mean time it is eaſie to judge that that would be a great prejudice to the Enemies of <hi>France,</hi> and that it would deprive them
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:44821:70"/>from a great advantage, which it is likely they might obtain by their Enemies want of Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; wherefore in ſuch a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable juncture, the Allies will not endure any thing to their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, nor that can impead their Enterprizes. It is much better for <hi>Denmark,</hi> immediately to embrace that party, as being its true Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, than to deferr doing ſo, 'till <hi>France</hi> has had a blow.</p>
            <p>The Moſt Chriſtian King rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kons much on the King of <hi>Poland</hi> his Allie, there is betwixt them a very great Commerce of Money, and of Letters, that is no News, every body knows it, though one ſhould not make it ones buſineſs to prye into it; thoſe Meſſengers which ſo frequently paſs to and fro ſhews it ſufficiently, and no body is ignorant that the <hi>French</hi> Intereſt is entirely predominant in that Court, That King Employs for the moſt part <hi>French</hi> Men for
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:44821:71"/>his Miniſters in the Foreign Courts. The Queen is ſtill <hi>French</hi> in her inclinations and heart, as well as by Birth; (that is a quality which all the Princeſſes of <hi>France</hi> carry along with them, when they are Married out of the Kingdom) they meddle with Affairs; and that which ſhe underſtands not well how to mannage, ſhe is inform'd in by Monſieur the Marqueſs of <hi>Bethune</hi> her Brother. The Grand <hi>Seignior</hi> has been infinitely oblig'd to him during the late Campaigns; and though that War would not produce any great advantage to the King of <hi>Poland,</hi> yet he is for no Truce, he has his particular Reaſons, which he is not oblig'd to tell: If that Prince after the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance of <hi>Vienna</hi> had gone for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards with his Victories, long ſince had the important Fortreſs of <hi>Caminieck</hi> been in his hands. <hi>France</hi> flatters him with words that are but wind, aſſuring him
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:44821:71"/>that it ſhall be put into his hands by agreement, but who knows whether it will in a little time be in a Condition of keeping that promiſe. It is an unhappineſs for <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> that <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIVth has found ſo much Credit in that Court, and that the <hi>French</hi> Coin is ſo well known in thoſe parts. It were well for Prince <hi>Jacob,</hi> if the King his Father did cleave more cloſely to the Emperor, than he has done ſince <hi>Vienna,</hi> and that preferring the General intereſt of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> to that of <hi>France,</hi> he ſhould give his helping hand to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a Truce, to prevent by that means <hi>Europe</hi> from falling into a greater Miſchief than it is lately got out of. But let us turn our ſelves towards its Deliverer.</p>
            <p>Though the <hi>Engliſh</hi> are a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which is naturally War-like, Undaunted, and whoſe Courage frequently runs even to raſhneſs, they loving that Liberty in which
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:44821:72"/>they are Born: yet it may be ſaid, that <hi>England,</hi> during the Reign of its two laſt Kings, has Conrribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the downfal of <hi>Europe</hi> into Slavery, when it could have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented it with one word, through a deceitful hope, that it could ſave it ſelf from ruine, either by the Situation of the Country, and by its Forces, or by the Illuſory pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of <hi>France.</hi> All the Princes of <hi>Europe</hi> have always pris'd very highly the Alliance with <hi>England,</hi> even in the time of the Emperor <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth, (as we have ſeen before) thoſe Kings have held the Ballance in <hi>Europe,</hi> ſo long as they have not ſwerv'd from their true intereſts, and that they have not ſold their freedom to <hi>France. Henry</hi> the VIIIth did compare <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>France</hi> to the two boles of a pair of Scales, that that ſide weigh'd it down on which he lean'd. He ſpoke juſtly, f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r the Monarchs of that Kingdom being
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:44821:72"/>well united with their Parliaments, may ſtile themſelves the Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of <hi>Chriſtendom:</hi> It is not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reaſon then that <hi>France</hi> has flatter'd them, during the two Reigns that have preceded this, and <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIVth thought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf at the top of all his De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>gns, when he did ſee <hi>James</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d on the Throne, making open p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ofeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Roman-Catholick Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, perhaps with a little more paſſion than became a King; but that was the weak ſide by which the <hi>French</hi> King would catch him, and detain him in his Bonds; for that Prince, ever ſubtle and crafty, did hit him on that ſide on which he was moſt ſenſible, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of his Honour, and againſt the inclination of the Nation, and the Parliaments expectations. Mean time <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIVth had ſo well manag'd his Allie, that it may be ſaid, he already Triumph'd over him; and that through all his
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:44821:73"/>Managements, Intreagues, and <hi>Lewis D'Ors,</hi> he was become Maſter of King <hi>James</hi> his Fortune, by the ſubtlety of his Miniſters, who lull'd him aſleep on ſpecious. Offers of Sixty Millions, and of 60000 Men, to ſupport him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Enemies, and even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his own People, if they would have reſiſted, and ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves free; <hi>France</hi> little caring for the evil conſequences that this Commerce could not but produce, ſo it did its own Buſineſs, and render'd that Prince odious to his Allies, and to his Neighbours, as well as to his own Subjects, who began to feel the ſmart of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious Council, either in their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, Laws, or Religion; and ſeeing themſelves preſs'd down by a Tirannical Authority, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotick Power of an obſeded and gained King, by <hi>France,</hi> and wholly devoted to its Intereſts, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have found themſelves conſtrain'd
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:44821:73"/>to prevent their falling into the ſame Predicament their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours were in, to have recourſe to their Liberator, that in being themſelves deliver'd, they might delive<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> all <hi>Europe</hi> alſo from that ſlavery in which it w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> going to fall, and to that pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er the Throne to the Prince o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Orange,</hi> and to the Princeſs his Spouſe, as the lawful Heirs to the Three Kingdoms; and God having granted the Nations Vows and Petition, he has ſo well conducted that Great Prince's Enterpriſe, that it may be ſaid, he has led him by the Hand, and ſeated him on that Throne that was deſigned for him without any effuſion of Blood. This Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle we have ſeen, but our Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſprings will ſcarce believe it; it is an happy and more than happy change, ſeeing that it will render a calm and quiet to all Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and that he reſtores to <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> its Liberty. It was <hi>William</hi>
               <pb n="144" facs="tcp:44821:74"/>the III. that Providence had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd, through the Aſſiſtance of the States of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ted Provinces, to be the glorious Inſtrument of ſo great a Work, capable to cauſe once more the dumb Son of <hi>Cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſus</hi> to ſpeak, if he were yet living. But in the place of that Prince, <hi>Europe,</hi> that was become in a manner Dumb, through thoſe great Evils that it ſuffer'd before-hand, has ſet up the Standard of Liberty and of Deliverance. Since that Prince and Princeſs of <hi>Orange</hi> have been Seated on the Throne, all Chriſtendom begins, as it were, to revive again; Catholicks and Proteſtants, all raiſe up their Heads againſt their Oppreſſor, as when a Tree is fallen, every body runs to take their ſhare of the Bows. But to accompliſh the Work, Two Things are requir'd; Firſt, a good and firm League amongſt the Chriſtian Princes, who have under-gone, and who
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:44821:74"/>ſtill fear to fall under the <hi>French</hi> Kings Uſurpation, ſhould he get off of this preſent danger, ſo that nothing may be able to diſſolve that Union, and that no private Intereſt, nor Elderſhip, ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail over the general Good, and that he who ſhall ſeparate from that Union, ſo neceſſary to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom, ſhould be look'd upon as a Perturbator, and a common Enemy, and ſet in the number of the Turks, and the <hi>French,</hi> to be ſet upon as a Deſerter, and Traitor to the general Good of <hi>Europe.</hi> That Neutrality have no Place in Chriſtendom; <hi>that he who is not for us is againſt us.</hi> Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly that League being ſo well Cemented, all the offers of <hi>France,</hi> nor the ſatisfaction that it might give to ſome of the Pretenders, nor being able to break the Union, it is moſt certain that all will bow to the Allies; that they ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:44821:75"/>Drums beating and Colours flying, into their Enemies Country, where they ought by all means to take up their Winter Quarters the next Seaſon, to prevent <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV's Forces from entring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Country of the Allies, as he deſigns, and to give him at Home ſo much Buſineſs, that he may not go ſeek for ſome elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where. For if they enter not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>France,</hi> but that the Allies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent themſelves with taking ſome Places which he has formerly ſeiz'd on, with a deſign to amuſer them to get time, as <hi>Mentz, Bonn, Keiſerwaert,</hi> and others, that are about his Kingdom; that would be doing nothing at all, ſeeing the King has ſtill his end, and that he holds thoſe Places but to buſie the Allies during this firſt Campaign, either to tire them, or to drain them through length of time, or to Alienate ſome. That is <hi>Lewis</hi>
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:44821:75"/>the XIV's chief end, and the beſt Advice that he could take in ſuch a preſſing juncture, in which he finds himſelf at preſent. But if that for his good, and for the ill of <hi>Europe,</hi> he can break down the Dike, though the Breach be never ſo ſmall, he will drown all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom, and the laſt evil would be worſe than the firſt. To avoid this miſchief, no Prince of the League ought to ſuffer any <hi>French</hi> Emiſſary in his Territories, they ought to be Baniſh'd as In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected Perſons, and not Pardon the very firſt that ſhall be found, not ſparing even the Church Men; thoſe are flying Plagues, who like ſtinking fleſh Flies, infect all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces they light on; it is a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Seed, which is to be rooted quite up.</p>
            <p>The Allies ought not to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd at the great number of Men there is in <hi>France,</hi> they are young
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:44821:76"/>Vipers that will eat a Paſſage through their Mothers Belly to get at Liberty: Not the Tenth Part of that great People have cauſe to be contented, and the moſt ſound part waits but for its Deliverance, on what Side ſoever; and it may be ſaid that <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. is not better belov'd in his Kingdom than <hi>James</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. was in his. It is certain, that when the Prince of <hi>Lorrain</hi> ſhall appear before his own Subjects, they will receive him with the ſame Joy that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have receiv'd the Prince of <hi>Orange:</hi> I ſay the ſame of <hi>Burgundy,</hi> and of the <hi>French</hi> County, and of divers other People, who wait but for the happy Moment of their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty.</p>
            <p>The Second thing to be done, is a powerful Fleet, which the King of <hi>England</hi> is to keep conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually at Sea, that in conjunction
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:44821:76"/>with that of the States General, he may be Maſter of the Sea, and not only give an Allarm on the Coaſts of <hi>France,</hi> but make a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent alſo in Two different places, ſo ſoon as poſſible it can be done; then will that Kingdom be in a Combuſtion, and the King of it will loſe the North, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what place firſt to Succour, as a City that the Fire ſeizes in all Places; and thoſe that ſhall Land there may be aſſur'd to be Seconded by a great number of the Inhabitants, all along that Coaſt, and from the Neighbouring Provinces. <hi>William</hi> the III. now Reigning, ought to be certain that his Predeceſſors have not for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing preſerv'd that Title of King of <hi>France;</hi> the Rights of Kings never grow out of Date, they are always Pupils, and at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to claim what has wrongfully been taken from them. So long
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:44821:77"/>as <hi>England</hi> ſhall ſubſiſt, the Kings will have a double Right to <hi>France,</hi> which will never be loſt ſo long as <hi>Henry</hi> the V. ſhall have any Succeſſors to the Crown of <hi>England;</hi> he was Son to <hi>Marga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> and ſhe Daughter to <hi>Philip le Bell,</hi> whoſe Sons de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceas'd without Succeſſors to the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> and that <hi>Henry,</hi> as a further Right, Married the Daughter of <hi>Charles</hi> the VI. Being come to <hi>France,</hi> it was decreed by the States of the Kindom, that he ſhould be their King after the Death of <hi>Charles</hi> the VI. and in that Quality the Queen his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Law, made him Heir of all her Means, and of the Crown of <hi>France.</hi> I am perſwaded, that there would not need any thing near ſo much to <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. to frame an irrevocable Pretenſion on <hi>England,</hi> and that the Royal Chamber of <hi>Metz</hi> would very
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:44821:77"/>readily confirm it without the leaſt trouble, but there is no ſuch thing; on the contrary, there has happen'd a time, in which all the deceits and ſubtleties of <hi>France</hi> begin very much to unſtitch, and to be thread-bare. <hi>William</hi> the III. has overturn'd the Bankers Tables, which the <hi>French</hi> King's Emiſſaries had ſet up in all places; their falſe Coin is no longer currant; their Money is cry'd down, their <hi>Lewis D'Ors,</hi> which were Worſhipped as the Heathen do their Puppets, are grown odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to honeſt People, at leaſt the occaſion of their Diſtribution; and they are no more capable to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt at this time, than is the Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of <hi>Sweede.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus <hi>France</hi> beginning to be cried down by all Chriſtendom, and to be ſlighted in all the Courts of the Princes of <hi>Europe,</hi> it has chang'd its Game, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to imitate thoſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:44821:78"/>Curtiſans, who being grown old and wither'd, are caſt off, and abandon'd by every body, who alter the Paſſion once had for them, which obliges them alſo to an alteration, in turning Biggots and Superſtitious, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to counterfeit <hi>Mary-Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen,</hi> thereby to regain that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem of the People which they had loſt by their debauched Lives. Thus <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. to draw on new Friends and Allies, the better to oppoſe himſelf to the King of <hi>Great Britain;</hi> and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving that all his Credit with the Catholick Princes is at an end, that none will any longer confide in him, and that his Maxims are cried down, he has taken in hand other Means, much more ſubtle than the precedent were; he no longer ſpeaks to them of his own Intereſts, but he now Proclaims to them, <hi>That they
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:44821:78"/>muſt come to the Aſſiſtance of the Catholick Religion.</hi> That it was aimed at, when King <hi>James</hi> his Ally was Attack'd; and that he has no other deſign of making War, but for the ſupport of that dear Religion, eſpecially by the re-eſtabliſhment of that Prince on his Throne; that if all the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks would but join with him, or remain Neuter, that he alone will undertake to Re-eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh him, and at the ſame time the Catholick Religion, in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> and after, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat, beat down Hereſie in its very Center. But all this while, <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIV. is far from telling what he conceals under thoſe ſpecious Pretences, which would be, that after he had pull'd down <hi>William</hi> the III. overcome the Proteſtant Princes, he would do the like to all the Roman Catholicks, one after another, and thus become Maſter of <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="154" facs="tcp:44821:79"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ain, that the diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of Religion has always been as a large and vaſt Abiſs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Catholick and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Princes, but the Cruelty and Perfidiouſneſs of the <hi>French,</hi> has fill'd up that Abiſs, and levell'd the way between them, and all difficulties are at preſent laid aſide. Even the <hi>French</hi> King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, unknowingly, has given a help in hand to the Buſineſs, with all his Power; for while he endeavours to perſwade all the World, that he has no other aim than to promote the Catholick Faith, and that he Preaches in all places his Converſions, that he importunes the Pope to join with him for the Defence of the Church, and juſt in the height of ſuch a fair Miſſion, in all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, he orders his Troops to enter into the Territories of the Catholick Princes, to Attack thoſe
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:44821:79"/>of the Prelates of the Church, and even to inſult the Pope, though Head of that Religion which he proteſts he would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, burning and deſtroying all over <hi>Germany,</hi> where his Troops but ſet their Foot, without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of Religion, nor of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Sacrificing to their Rage the moſt Sacred Places, their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolence not ſparing ſo much as the Monaſteries of the Virgins, devoted to the Service of God, nor their impiety the Image of our Saviour, and that of the holy Virgin his Mother, which they have Treated with the greateſt Indignation and irreverence that any Atheiſt could have been guilty of, acting in all places like Men that had no Faith, and that acknowledg'd no God; and all this too, as the whole World knows, againſt the promis'd Faith of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and Capitulations, which they
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:44821:80"/>own they have agreed to, but to enter the further, and with more eaſe into Places, and to put in Execution their Wicked and Pernicious Deſigns; the King threatning to Caſhier thoſe Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers that ſhould not execute with all barbarouſneſs, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly with the laſt extremity, the Orders of the Court; as if they had been ſent to put an end to the Would by Fire, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the appointed time by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence.</p>
            <p>After all this, how can ſo cruel and ſo inhumane a Prince take up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him the Title of <hi>Moſt Chriſtian,</hi> and while that by an over-plus of Crimes he joyns with the <hi>Turks</hi> to exterminate and ruine <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> aſſuring thoſe <hi>Infidels,</hi> that he has not taken up Arms but to come to their Aſſiſtance, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure them t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to recover what they have loſt in <hi>Hungary,</hi>
               <pb n="157" facs="tcp:44821:80"/>and to return before <hi>Vienna.</hi> It is no ſmall trouble to that <hi>Moſt Chriſtian King</hi> to have miſt his oportunity, during the laſt Siege of <hi>Vienna,</hi> not to have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd with his Army (which was ready at hand) into <hi>Germany,</hi> without expecting as he did the taking of <hi>Vienna;</hi> but he then believing the loſs of it inevitable, he thought he ſhould deferr his March but a few days, and the better conceal his wicked De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, and that then the pretence would not only be plauſible, but juſt alſo, to all appearance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it had been to prevent the <hi>Turks</hi> from entring any further; but at the ſame time to render himſelf Maſter of the reſt of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> and of all the Ernpire alſo; which ſhould have been his ſhare towards the defraying of the Wars; ſo he had divided with <hi>Mahomet</hi> the IVth all the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:44821:81"/>both Catholick and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, of <hi>Germany.</hi> If after all theſe Contrivances, one may ſtile ones ſelf a Zealot to the Catholick Religion, I referr it to the Judgment of the Pope; let us then ſay rather, that he is a <hi>Wolf in Sheeps Cloathings,</hi> cover'd with a falſe Piety, to devour the Chriſtian Princes one after another; That was Cardinal <hi>Richlieu</hi>'s Maxime, <hi>Not to value what he Promiſed,</hi> nor <hi>his Faith in the obſervation of Treaties, ſo he but ſerv'd the</hi> French <hi>Intereſt:</hi> And doubtleſs it is from thoſe rare Leſſons, that this Zealous <hi>French</hi> King has ſo well improv'd, and which he endeavours to imitate ſo exactly, before thoſe of the Goſpel, which <hi>forbid us to do to others, that which we would not have done to our ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if we look on Buſineſſes
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:44821:81"/>nearer at hand, we ſhall not wonder at the King's preſſing for the Re-eſtabliſhment of <hi>James</hi> the Second, and that he leaves no ſtone unmov'd, to reſeat him on the Throne: We ſhall find at laſt that it is not ſo much Religion as Intereſt that moves him to it, and that the return of that Prince to his Kingdom, is moſt neceſſary for him, much more than the Eſtabliſhment of the Cardinal of <hi>Fuſtemberg,</hi> in the Arch-Biſhoprick of <hi>Colen.</hi> It cannot be believ'd that it is the natural affection which he has for thoſe two Princes that make him act, or the Zeal to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, as he publiſhes, but his Ambition, and the Preſervation of his Kingdom. For if Prince <hi>Joſeph Clement,</hi> and the preſent King of <hi>England,</hi> would but em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Party of <hi>France,</hi> and Unite themſelves with that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch,
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:44821:82"/>he would ſend the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal to <hi>Strasbourg,</hi> and King <hi>James</hi> where he was in <hi>Cromwel</hi>'s time, or into ſome corner of the State of <hi>Modena;</hi> and if the Town of <hi>Algier</hi> wou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>w ſend Ships into the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he would not only ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> with their Prizes in h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rts, but would give them Liberty alſo to build a <hi>Moſq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere, if that Town ſhould require it. I ſee no greater diff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ulty nor Crime in that, than in lending his Forces to Re-build ſome in <hi>Hungary,</hi> and to pull down the Chriſtian Churches. Theſe are then the fruits of this great Zeal. of which the <hi>French</hi> boaſted in <hi>Rome,</hi> and at <hi>Madrid.</hi> Now let us turn our faces towards Truth. It is not Religion that puſhes the <hi>French</hi> King, but he has the Shepherd at his heels, the Nets are ſpread on all parts
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:44821:82"/>for him, and he has no proſpect of eſcaping; and in that dread he is, he would embrace the <hi>Alcoran,</hi> if he ſaw it would ſhelter him from the new King of <hi>England</hi>'s Reſentments, whom he has reaſon to fear, as the moſt dreadful and moſt powerful Enemy that he has at preſent, or ever had; with whom there is no Compoſition to be made, though <hi>Lewis</hi> the XIVth ſhould return four times as much as he has Uſurped from him, when he was yet but Prince of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range.</hi> Perceiving then, that by the means of <hi>William</hi> the Third he has all <hi>Europe</hi> on his hands, and that he muſt leave ſome Fleeces behind him, no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der he extends his hands (though in vain,) towards the one, and the other, to find out a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diator, to draw him out of that Danger in which he finds him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf:
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:44821:83"/>But he, having taken his Eternal farewel of all Faith and Honeſty, and it having abandon'd him, every body does the ſame, daring no longer to truſt to him, 'till firſt he has been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priv'd of his Savageneſs, of his Ambition, of his Pride, and of his inſatiable deſire of Uſurping the Goods of his Neighbours; and that is what will not hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, 'till he has firſt been hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled by Loſſes, either in his Armies, or of ſome of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces; and that he has been oblig'd to reſtore to every one that which he has ſtoln from them; and that is what may be advantageous, and neceſſary for his poor People, and to all <hi>Europe.</hi> In vain he Flatters him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with an accommodation with ſome of the Allies, whom he pretends to divide from the Union in which we ſee them
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:44821:83"/>at preſent, and by that means to draw himſelf out of the Briers.</p>
            <p>This King has been inexo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to the Cries of the Poor, whom he has Ruin'd and Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented; of the Widdows and Orphans, whom he has ſtript Naked; the Heavens will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn it upon him, as well as all his Enemies; who will return him double the Evil which he has done, and will force him to ſwallow down the bitter Fruits of his Ambition, and breach of Faith, and to Diſgorge all his Uſurpations which he has Baptis'd with the ſpecious Title of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts; and return to his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects that Liberty of Conſcience, and places of Hoſtages which he has forc'd from them, againſt the Faith of Edicts, under the pretence of Converſions; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore to all his People in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:44821:84"/>the General States, for the ſurety of their Perſons, and Means, whereas they now groan under the heavy preſſure of the Intendants theſe are Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, which our new <hi>Hercules</hi> muſt vanquiſh; which God has gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to free <hi>Europe</hi> from that ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very in which part of it was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready reduc'd, and wherein the reſt was going to fall, the Irons being already ſet in the Fire for it, by the means of <hi>James</hi> the II. who abandoning his own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, and that of his Nation, had given his Conſent and Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance to the ruine of <hi>Europe;</hi> and had enter'd into a League with the Uſurper, to make it to fall under the ſlavery with more eaſe and greater expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But the Heavens, who have granted the Vows and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of all <hi>Europe,</hi> has broken thoſe Chains by the means of
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:44821:84"/>a Republick, of which he had made his Prey; for it may be ſaid, without ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>geration, that the States of the United Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces have given the firſt blow to break thoſe Shackles, through the Aſſiſtance they have given of Money, of Forces, and of Ships, to the King of <hi>England,</hi> when he was yet but Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> Wherefore <hi>Europe</hi> ought to conſider them as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Cauſe of its Deliverance, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorer of its Liberty, the Refuge of all the Affl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cted, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>etr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at of thoſe whom <hi>Lewi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the XIVth had Perſecuted, and ſtripp'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; and the Azilum of all good People, who ought in gratitude to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard their Lives for the Support of a State, who has free'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem from the Lyon's jaws, and has receiv'd them with ſo much Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity and Charity, which doubtleſs ſhall be the Cannons
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:44821:85"/>with which they ſhall deſtroy their Enemies, and the Heavens will render them Victorious, and their Names ſhall laſt to the laſt of Ages.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:44821:85"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
